<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The parasynagogue paragorized, or, A parenetical confutation of the epidemical error which asserteth, separation from parochial church-communion : demonstrating their practice, who on the Lords day neglect the publick exercises of divine worship in their parochial congregations, and frequent (cæteris paribus) other churches, to be anti-scriptural / by John Lesly ...</title>
            <author>Lesly, John, d. 1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 108 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47777</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1171</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11754</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12425869</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12425869</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61849</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47777)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61849)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 944:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The parasynagogue paragorized, or, A parenetical confutation of the epidemical error which asserteth, separation from parochial church-communion : demonstrating their practice, who on the Lords day neglect the publick exercises of divine worship in their parochial congregations, and frequent (cæteris paribus) other churches, to be anti-scriptural / by John Lesly ...</title>
                  <author>Lesly, John, d. 1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 165 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Maxey ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Pages 26-41 and 116-135 from Dr. William's Library, London copy spliced at end.</note>
                  <note>Table of contents: p. [9]-[11]</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [12]</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sunday --  Biblical teaching.</term>
               <term>Worship --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61849:1"/>
            <p>THE PARASYNAGOGUE PARAGORIZED.</p>
            <p>OR A Parenetical confutation of the Epidemical Error, which aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Separation from Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial Church-communion.</p>
            <p>Demonſtrating Their practice, who on the Lords day neglect the publick Exerciſes of Divine Worſhip in their Parochial Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and frequent <hi>(caeteris paribus)</hi> other Churches, to be Anti-ſcriptural.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Leſly;</hi> Miniſter of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel at St. <hi>Michaels,</hi> neer St. <hi>Albans</hi> in <hi>Hertfordſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Maxey,</hi> in <hi>Thames-ſtreet.</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraphs">
            <pb facs="tcp:61849:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Cor. 3.4.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhile one ſaith, I am of</hi> Paul; <hi>and another, I am of</hi> Apollo; <hi>are ye not carnal?</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Clemens Rom.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <bibl>Cyprian. de Lapſis.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Non jungitur Eccleſiae, qui ab Evangelio ſeparatur.</p>
               <bibl>Baſil. ad Amphiloch.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:61849:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Honourable, WILLIAM LENTHALL Eſquire, Maſter of the Rolls, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honorable, and Honored Sir.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Sufficient A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology for my bold ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture of preſenting this part of my poor endeavors unto the publick view, may be an obſervation of the heathen; that when the Lord is pleaſed to viſit a Nation with the ſword, or the like judgment,<note place="margin">Eurip. apud Sarah l. <hi>11</hi> pag <hi>498.</hi>
               </note> then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; the worſhip of
<pb facs="tcp:61849:3"/>
God is weakened, and men will not honor him as they ſhould. Not ſo much for your particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination toward mee doe I make mention of your Name before this Treatiſe: as for that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Conceſſion and Homologie, That the publick inferres the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate benefit: In the peace of the City,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jerem</hi> 29 7</note> ye ſhall have peace: For I feele my ſelfe no ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe member of thoſe bodies, which out of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers experiences chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge an intereſt in your Honours moſt favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Integrity and Love, which you have alwaies borne to Gods Glory, Chriſts Goſpel, and all good Cauſes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="tcp:61849:3"/>
you may bee charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The greateſt great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath no greater Honour belonging to it, then to be an <hi>Abrech</hi> to Perſons, Bookes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.43</note> and Cauſes of this Nature. Such Cedars have their ſpreadth and tallneſſe to ſhelter ſuch Fowles of the Heaven under their ſhadow. It was the pious reſolution of <hi>Luther</hi> in one of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles; <hi>Inveniar ſanè Superbus, Avarus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luther ad. Stanpit.</note> 
               <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulter, Homicida, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>papa, &amp; omnium viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arum reus, modo impij ſilentij non arguar, dum Dominus patitur:</hi> That hee had rather be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any thing, then bee accuſed of wicked ſilence in Gods cauſe. And
<pb facs="tcp:61849:4"/>
wee know, that the more diſhonoured and trampled upon any cauſe of God<hi>'s</hi> is, the more hee expects that wee ſhould appeate for it. Now leſt any man ſhould bring a bloud-ſhot eye, to make all appeare of a wrong colour; that I have made no particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Perſon my Aime or Adverſary, my witneſſe is in heaven,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 16 19</note> and my record on high. But becauſe loſſe of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation followeth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacie in Errour,<note place="margin">Camero p. <hi>286.</hi> in fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lio.</note> I have done my poore endeavour to proclaime Gods will. If any doe demurre, or obſtinately perſiſt, or reſiſt, they may remember they erre
<pb facs="tcp:61849:4"/>
not without warning.</p>
            <p>Common Ingenuity com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth mee thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to acknowledge, what you have done for one, that hath no wittie In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuations for extract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of your favours, nor Impudency enough to returne them in flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries: yea, who had ſuch obſtructions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene his heart and his tongue, that hee could ſcarce expreſſe the leaſt part of his Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, much leſſe is hee able to make you a requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal.</p>
            <p>But the Lord of Lords grant, that you may find all favour in the eyes of God and Man, that all true Happineſſe
<pb facs="tcp:61849:5"/>
may be multiplyed upon you and yours, and crown you with eternity. So prayeth,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours obliged and humble Servant in the Lord, <hi>JOHN LESLY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:61849:5"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 1.</hi>THere is a neceſſity of oppoſing Errors: and a ſpecial neceſſity of oppoſing the Errour of Indetermined Church-Communion.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi>The late Original of this Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror. Some mſchiefes of it are indigitated. A Motive to reſiſt them.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi>Parochial Church-communion is a duty implanted by Nature, and a Moral and Solemn part of Divine Worſhip.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi>All Chriſtians are to joyne themſelves to ſome particular viſible Church, when the Lord offereth occaſion.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi>We are bound to hearing in our own determined Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, Neceſſitate praecepti.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:61849:6"/>
                  <hi>6.</hi>God aſſigneth unto every or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Paſtor a portion of his people, to be instructed by him.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi>Separation from determined Church-communion is repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>1 Cor. 1.12.</hi> and <hi>3. ver. 4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi>The Lord commandeth to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him Orderly: which is not obſerved in Indetermined Church-communion.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi>We are bound to hearing in our particular Congregations, by Chriſts Doctrine and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi>We are bound to the duty of Determined Church-communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by the cuſtome of Apoſtolick and primitive times.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11.</hi>Reaſon teacheth that Indeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined Church-communion is carnal glorying in the worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or excellency of other Paſtors.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12.</hi>Some ſinfull effects and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequents of Parochial or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational Church-ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</item>
               <item>The cauſes which men pretend for Separation from Parochial Church-communion, are fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous
<pb facs="tcp:61849:6"/>
and invalid. And,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13.</hi>Firſt, indetermined Church-communion, is no part, but an abuſe of Chriſtian Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14.</hi>Secondly, Separation from Church-communion for the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors knowne inſufficiency, or Scandalous life, may be lawful. Otherwiſe it is lamentable, if not intolerable and impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15.</hi>Thirdly, Other imaginary, and imaginated pretences are anſwered.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16.</hi>Serious and frequent admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ought to be inculcated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this error.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17.</hi>Some Antidotes againſt the Infection of Separation from Parochial Church-communion.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18.</hi>The Concluſion.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:61849:7"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>IN the Book.</hi> pag. <hi>4.</hi> lin. <hi>26.</hi> for <hi>Cannons,</hi> read <hi>Canons.</hi> p. <hi>5.</hi> l. <hi>16</hi> for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. <hi>6.</hi> l. <hi>9.</hi> for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. <hi>9.</hi> l. <hi>10.</hi> for <hi>were</hi> read went. In Marg. l. <hi>24</hi> for <hi>Arm. de,</hi> read <hi>Ameſ. de.</hi> p. <hi>10.</hi> in Marg. l. <hi>16. Jer. 2.14.</hi> is wanting. p. <hi>13.</hi> in Marg. l. <hi>10.</hi> for <hi>Ceſerenſ,</hi> read <hi>Ceſtrenſ.</hi> p. <hi>15.</hi> l. <hi>6.</hi> for <hi>livng,</hi> read <hi>living.</hi> p <hi>16.</hi> l. <hi>8</hi> put out <hi>and.</hi> l. <hi>22.</hi> for <hi>exacteth,</hi> reade <hi>enacteth.</hi> p. <hi>31.</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi> put out <hi>the.</hi> p. <hi>44</hi> l. penult, for <hi>Ceriſtians,</hi> read <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi> p. <hi>47.</hi> l. <hi>4. are</hi> is wanting. l. <hi>5</hi> for <hi>allay,</hi> read <hi>alloy.</hi> p. <hi>73.</hi> l. <hi>22.</hi> for <hi>Orthadox,</hi> r. <hi>Orthodox:</hi> for <hi>Heto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodox,</hi> r. <hi>Heterodox.</hi> p. <hi>80.</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi> for <hi>apprehend,</hi> read <hi>apprehended.</hi> l. <hi>27. this</hi> is wanting. p. <hi>105.</hi> l. <hi>15. not</hi> is wanting. p. <hi>111.</hi> l. <hi>18. the</hi> is wanting. p. <hi>124.</hi> l. <hi>7.</hi> put out <hi>not.</hi> lin. <hi>22.</hi> for <hi>Meditaion</hi> read <hi>Mediation.</hi> p. <hi>139.</hi> l. <hi>11.</hi> for <hi>nulla,</hi> read <hi>nulli.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61849:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Paraſynagogue Paragorized.</hi> OR, A Parenetical Confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Epidemical Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, which aſſerteth, <hi>Separation from Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Church-Communion.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> There is a Neceſſity of oppoſing Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors: and a ſpecial Neceſſity of oppoſing the Error of indetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Church-communion.</head>
               <p n="1">§. 1. <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the infinite Goodneſſe of the Lord, that <hi>in wrath he remembers mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy:</hi> For my part,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hab.</hi> 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> I look upon it as a ſpecial mercy, that although we live in times, in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61849:8"/>
which the Truth is oppoſed and blaſphemed more then ever before; yet the Faithful have liberty to ſpeak and write in defence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. I wiſh that all orthodox Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians (who have more leiſure, greater helps and endowments then their Brethren) had more zeal to improve this liberty for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the Truth; and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that it is wretched,<note place="margin">Tertull. de Cor. Mil. c <hi>1</hi> Ruff. Hiſt. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi> Sozom. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi> Rev. <hi>21.8</hi> Rav. in vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce <hi>Timidus</hi> Matth. <hi>10.28, 33</hi>
                  </note> in time of peace to be fierce as Lyons, but in the combate to be fearful like Harts. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> as well as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul,</hi> had a great conflict for the Church of Chriſt. <hi>Alexander</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> was blamed by many for his too ſlow confuting <hi>Arius</hi> his Hereſie. The Fearful, who are threatned to <hi>have their part in the lake that burneth with fire and brimſtone,</hi> are they, <hi>Qui veritatem Evangelii agnitam abnegant, aut profiteró nolunt, metu mortis vel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittendarum facultatum;</hi> ſaith <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanel.</hi> Who <hi>deny</hi> the known Truth of the Goſpel, or will not <hi>profeſſe</hi> it: Or, who at any time do evil, or omit good againſt the light of Conſcience, for fear of danger; ſay our learned Engliſh Annota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:61849:8"/>
The Authors of moſt of theſe Errors and Blaſphemies which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witch the ſouls of our people, are but little more to be blamed, then they that do profeſſe the Truth, (being endowed with gifts and helps) who ſuffer them to walk a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad without check or controule: It is but a ſlender diſcharge of our Duty,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.1, 2 <hi>Jude</hi> 3. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.9, 11</note> to cry out againſt Errors and Hereſies, and never to contend, nor convince men what Truth and Error is.</p>
               <p n="2">§. 2. Though I meddle with no Controverſie but with great reluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancie and diſtaſte;<note place="margin">Intellectus dominatur Appetitui. Scot. in <hi>3.</hi> d. <hi>33.</hi> aed. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> yet now I am in a manner conſtrained, upon two conſiderations: which may be my Apologie for the publication of this imperfect Piece: Firſt, As mans <hi>Intellect</hi> naturally abhorreth Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and a ſanctified man doth dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly abhor Errour in things Divine; ſo doth hee moſt of all abhor the corruption of the Vitals, and thoſe Errors which have a potent influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon the Heart and Life, as this which I oppoſe moſt evidently hath: Miſtakes we all have, and ſhall have; but the more they ſtop the motions of the heart and hand,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61849:9"/>
the more dangerous are they: The ſecond is,<note place="margin">Doctrina eſt ſpecies Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emoſynae, Camero p. <hi>90.</hi>
                  </note> The common excuſe or argument of the Times, <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> and <hi>Providence:</hi> which how far they may juſtifie me, I muſt leave to the Judge of all men; being ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged as a Paſtor, as a Friend, as a Chriſtian, to tender my beſt aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance for relief of the Truth.</p>
               <p>Though the crudity and weakneſſe of this writing be ſuch then, as ſhould prohibit the publication, yet it may he uſeful to Country People, who moſt commonly are ſubject to this Error. Had I writ it for the uſe of the Learned, I would have tryed to make it fitter for their uſe; and if I could not, I would have ſuppreſſed it.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">Conc. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levit. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>24, 25.</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no <hi>416</hi>
                  </note>§. 3. The Shepherds part and duty is, to <hi>defend his Flock</hi> from Dogs, Wolves, Thieves; which if he neglected to do, he incurred the loſſe of his Office; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the publick and ancient Cannons of the Church.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.11</note> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.38.</note> But if the Flock deſpiſing their Shepherd, do miſcarry, they muſt thank them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for it.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.27</note> When the beautiful Order of the Church is broken,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zech.</hi> 11.10</note> then the Flock cannot but be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61849:9"/>
by Seducers; who ever corrupt the purity of Doctrine and Dicipline, and marre the beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful face of the Church. The words of the Lord. Ezech. 1.38. <hi>When I ſay unto the wicked, Thou ſhalt ſurely die, and thou giveſt him not warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor ſpeakeſt to warn the wicked from his wicked way to ſave his life, the ſame wicked man ſhall die in his iniquity, but his blood will I require at thine hand:</hi> Theſe words ſhould ſeem to Paſtor and People, not ſo much words, as thunderbolts;<note place="margin">Homer Ili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad. <hi>2</hi>
                  </note> and therefore unto the obſtinate, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, this Text will one day be terrible. For the Lord applyeth this threatning, not only to every particular impenitent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but every negligent Paſtor in the perſon of <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> that he may take to heart his duty, and his dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. The ſame charge is iterated, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 33.6. Signifying that Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiſts from Church-Communion in their proper and Parrochial Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations (in which they ſhould take warning from their appointed Paſtor) ſhall not eſcape puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though the Watchman be negligent; but if the Watchman
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61849:10"/>
blow the trumpet, and the Flock or Sinner will not then come, and hear, and obey, he ſhall incurre double puniſhment. The Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man then muſt anſwer for his part, for the blood of all that periſh through his default and negligence, to whom I ſay,<note place="margin">Homer Ili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> as he in the Poet; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; Wretched man, thou ſhouldſt not fear to tel men of their evil doing, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of their Church-ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="4">§. 4. Sinners are hardly brought to the ſight and ſenſe of their ſins: And therefore Paſtors muſt bring the ſins of their people upon the Stage,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.2. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.20 <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.31.</note> that they cannot deny them: as did the Prophets and Apoſtles. Better ſo, then for the people, (not knowing their ſin, that it is an horrible thing) to find how fearful a thing it is to fall into the hands of the living God. A Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.13.</note> that hath not grace in him to reprove ſinners, is like <hi>Salt that hath loſt his ſavour:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, he is become fooliſh. For the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſavourineſſe of ſalt is (as <hi>Euthymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> ſaith) <hi>Debilitas mordacitatis ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius;</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:61849:10"/>
The weakneſſe of its ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimony. Wee have many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of the Lords ſevere ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice againſt them that ſwerve aſide in the leaſt things,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.7. <hi>Levit.</hi> 10.1. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.4. &amp;c,</note> from the ſtrict rule of his Word, that concerne his Worſhip, and follow their owne wills and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions; though they have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo good a pretence for it: Tender hearts by judgements on others, are brought the more to fear God, leſt the ſame Judgements ſhould befall them: and to diſcerne, how failing about heavenly things (chiefly in his Worſhip) doth much incenſe Gods wrath.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:61849:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The late original of this Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror: Some miſchiefs of it are indigitated. A Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to reſiſt them.</head>
               <p n="1">§. 1 FIrſt it is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, That the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and practice of ſome men of ſpecial account in the Church of God, hath been, that Separatiſts are unworthy the honor of any ſet Conflict,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16 <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> and publick Confutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; But Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in many places knew Satans method bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: Satan ſeems ſomewhat ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fac'd at firſt, asks but ſome ſmall trifle; give him but that, he will be ready for greater points. If hee win ground in the Ceremonies, then he will abuſe the Sacrament. For when the Corinthians had ſit covered at Prayer a while, they grew even as unreverent at the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, which the Apoſtle was
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61849:11"/>
fain to rebuke. Then we are to reprove leſſer Errors at firſt, as the Apoſtle did: We are to think the Wiſe mans counſel worth the following, <hi>Ne ſit tibi minimum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> 
                  <hi>non negligere minima.</hi> Count it no ſmall matter, not to neglect ſmall matters. What ſo ſmall as an haire? When theſe ſmall hairs went from <hi>Samſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Judg.</hi> 16.19</note> his ſtrength left him. Moreover, leſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much ſilence ſhould be interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Conſent, or beget too great confidence in men of the goodneſſe of their cauſe, and others ſhould ſtumble at their vaunts;<note place="margin">Cam. p. <hi>322.</hi> in fol. Mareſ. Coll. Theol. d. <hi>17.</hi> Sect. <hi>9.</hi> Ved. Arc. Arm. part <hi>1</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>meſ. de Conſc. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi> Ruth. Due Right p. <hi>220</hi> &amp;c. Blake Cov c. <hi>31.</hi>
                  </note> I would deſire the Reader, for his full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to peruſe learned <hi>Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro, Mareſius, Vedelius,</hi> Dr. <hi>Ames,</hi> Mr. <hi>Rutherford,</hi> Mr. <hi>Blake,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reverend Divines: by whom he may be informed of his Duty in the danger of this ſin. For it is not my purpoſe at this time to diſcourſe, in what caſes it is lawful to ſeparate from a Church: much leſſe is it my buſineſſe to ſpeak of the incredible and deteſtable Church ſeparation, practiſed by Atheiſts, Epicures, Hereticks, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines, &amp;c. in theſe times,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61849:12"/>
                  <hi>Who walk after their own ungodly luſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jude</hi> 19.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſeparate themſelves, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſenſual, having not the Spirit: Whoſe judgement lingreth not,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 13.13.</note> 
                  <hi>nor their damnation ſlumber.</hi> But my buſineſſe is to admoniſh thoſe, who profeſſe they know God;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Having a form of godlineſſe, but in this deny the power thereof: That the Lord might give them repentance to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of the truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">§. 2. This premiſed: This Error of Church ſeparation, is by birth and Original, like unto Iſrael in her worſt condition: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Jer. 2.14.</note> a Home-borne ſlave; called by the Latines, <hi>Verna;</hi> i. e. <hi>Vere vilis natas,</hi> of a vile Original. Among the Heathen it was a reproachful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, to worſhip their gods with any new Adoration. And for that very thing the Athenians <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, were bitterly jeered by their Comicks; and particularly <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> reproved <hi>Aeſchines,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Strabo Geogr. l. <hi>10</hi> p. <hi>471.</hi>
                  </note> ſaith <hi>Strabo.</hi> Wee then ſhould fear, that vengeance denounced againſt the final im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitency of Revolters in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, doth not only concerne A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtates,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61849:12"/>
openly denying Chriſt; but, as <hi>Fulgentius</hi> well noteth,<note place="margin">Fulgent. ad Thraſ. l. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> him alſo, <hi>Qui ſilentio firmat errorem,</hi> who by ſilence confirmeth any Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and by holding his peace doth not confirme the Truth: <hi>Divinam contumeliam qui non refutavit, acu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulat:</hi> He that repelleth not Gods diſhonour,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.26.</note> (what he poſſibly can) addeth to it. The negligent or ſleepy Centinel betrayeth his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Tent. And now, leſt here I ſhould ſeem ſingular, I will expreſſe the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate Birth and Nativity of it, in the words of learned <hi>Honorius Reggius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Honor. Reg. de Statu Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glia. p. <hi>95.</hi>
                  </note> who hath collected a hundred and eighty Errors (out of Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> his <hi>Gangrene,</hi> and other late Writers) practiſed in <hi>England,</hi> ſince the year 1640, and communicated them unto forraign Nations: of which this is the 125 Error; <hi>Partem Libertatis Chriſtianae eſſe, non audire proprium Miniſtrum; ſed ubi libeat, &amp; â quo plus commodi ſperetur:</hi> That it is a part of Chriſtian Liberty, not to hear our own Miniſter; but to hear where one liketh beſt, and from whom we hope for moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:61849:13"/>§ 3 The miſchief of the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice I here oppoſe, lieth not in the bare error of judgment, but in the unchriſtian Diviſion and Aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which thence ſloweth, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Humility and Love, which is the viſible character of Chriſtians.<note place="margin">Evagr. Hiſt l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi> in Henotico Zenon. Imp.</note> Alas, the hideous Doctrines, the contemned Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, the unheard of wickedneſs that this Doctrine hath produced! the reproached and ſlandred Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, the weak that are ſcandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, the Profeſſors apoſtatized, the Profane hardned, the Enemy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting; all theſe do deſcribe it more plainly to us, then words can do, and cry aloud in the ears of God and good men. Hence is all this Atheiſm amongſt us, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying or not having a God; this Apoſtaſie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38 <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.16</note> in drawing back and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtranging our ſelves from God: this Profaneneſſe, in refuſing the Creator, that we may enjoy the Creature. How fruitful are we in monſtruous ſins, from the loweſt ſtep of Semi-ſeparatiſm, to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt pitch of Rantiſm? Which ſhould produce all manner of At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations to the Truth of Chriſt,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61849:13"/>
againſt the Errors and Blaſphemies occaſioned by this practice. But if we cannot ſee it at home, we may hear of it from abroad; from the pens of Proteſtant Divines, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king obſervation of the ſtate of the Church in <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Honor. Reg. de St. Eccl. in Angl. p. <hi>1</hi> Theologi Ceſtrenſ. in Atteſtatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſua, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſa Anno <hi>1648.</hi> Marc. in Diſp. ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quot. &amp;c.</note> who give this ſad, yet true report unto the world, That <hi>England</hi> in four years ſpace is become an heap and ſink of all Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, Sects; no Province from the beginning of the world, ever brought forth in ſo ſhort a ſpace, ſo many monſtrous Hereſies, as this. Can any man name any age ſince the Apoſtles, among all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Hereſies that ſtill invaded the Church, that ever had ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Maligners of the Miniſtry in general, and that ſtruck ſo ragingly at the very ſtanding of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, as the Church-Separatiſts in this age have done, and ſtill do? and that in ſuch numbers? Nay, hath Chriſt any thing that he may enjoy unqueſtioned among us? As he may not have a Miniſter, ſo he muſt not an Ordinance; not a Day, not a Duty, not ſo much as his Deity among us. For Opinion once ſeeded in Error,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61849:14"/>
ſhoots out into Hereſie, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome growth, in time into Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy.</p>
               <p n="4">§ 4 What then? Muſt a true Chriſtian ſtand by, and ſee the Cauſe of Chriſt, like a Foot-ball in the midſt of a crowd of Boyes, toſt about in contention, from one to another; and ſpurned about in the dirt, driving it on to the goal of their private intereſts and delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded fancies? Truly, it is not ſo eaſie for gracious diſpoſitions to turne off the publick calamities of Gods Church. Where is the policy (I ſay not Chriſtianity) of our times?<note place="margin">Socrat. Hiſt. l. <hi>5.</hi> Praer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</note> Which ſhould mind us, that, <hi>Calamitatum Reip. &amp; Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae eſt communio &amp; viciſſitudo.</hi> No man can do other, then loſe his private felicities in the common diſtreſſes of the Church. To avoid then all occaſions of publick Service for the Church un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of Humility or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſeneſſe, ſpeaks (too broadly) the deliquent Refractory. Your Anchoret, that digs his grave in Speculation meerly, and your Mole that is earthed wholly in an affected ſolitarineſs, are not liable
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61849:14"/>
ſo properly to obſcurity, as death. And we find an Apoplexy and Sleep no leſſe on their endeavors, then in their names. Indeed ſuch Silk-worms ſpin themſelves into Flies, diſani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, heartleſſe Flies, livng neither for Church nor Commonwealth. So that he that retreats at any Alarm or Summons of God for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon affaires of the Church, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy himſelfe in his ſolitary ends, runs himſelf on the ſhelves of that rough cenſure of <hi>Athanaſius;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Athanaſius ad Dracont Part <hi>2</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. ult.</note> 
                  <hi>Vereor ne dum propter te fugis; prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alios ſis in periculo apud Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num:</hi> To ſtand by, and to give aime only whilſt others ſhoot, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimes thy lazineſſe, if not thy im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency. If therefore this thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther implore thy aide (ſo <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> counſels his <hi>Eudoxius</hi>) on the one ſide, hand not with Ambition;<note place="margin">Auguſt. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. <hi>81.</hi>
                  </note> on the other, lean not to a lazie refuſal: Weigh not thine own i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleneſſe with the neceſſities and greatneſſe of her burthens, to which (whilſt ſhe is in travel) if no good men will adminiſter their help, <hi>Certe quomodo naſceremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni non inveniretis,</hi> God muſt then invent new ways for our new birth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:61849:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III</hi> Parochial Church-communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is a Duty implanted by Nature, and a Moral and Solemn part of Divine Worſhip.</head>
               <p n="1">§ 1 AND here I profeſſe, and I would not ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, in which I am ſingular: I have ſo much childiſh fear, as ſcarce to dare to walk in publick where I am alone. The Topick therefore whence I intend (God willing) to raiſe my Reaſons, for a due and dutiful obſervation of Parochial Church-communion, ſhall be the ſame threefold cord, with which <hi>Tertullian</hi> proſecuted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Subject:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4.12</note> that is, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Scripture, Nature, and Diſcipline. By theſe three I hope to demonſtrate, that Scripture en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acteth this Duty for a Law, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:61849:15"/>
eſtabliſheth it, and Diſcipline exacteth Obedience to it. As Nature,<note place="margin">Tertul. de Veland. Virg. c. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note> Scripture and Diſcipline are the Lords, (ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi>) ſo whatever is contrary to them is not the Lords. Let that be unto thee Scripture, Nature and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, which thou findeſt ratified by God; as thou art commanded,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.21</note> 
                  <hi>To prove all things, and to hold faſt that which is good. Cui ex his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuctudo opinionis profit, vel quis diverſa ſententiae color eſt?</hi> What can cuſtom of opinion profit any of theſe, or what pretence is there for any contrary judgment? ſaith that Father.</p>
               <p>And firſt I begin with the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of Nature, becauſe God hath premiſed Nature to be thy Teacher,<note place="margin">Tertul. de Reſurrect. Carn. c. <hi>12.</hi> Tertul. de Cor. Milit. c. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> being afterwards about to ſend the Scripture, that thou mighteſt the more eaſily believe the Scripture, being firſt Natures Scholar; and whatſoever is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Nature, deſerveth by all men to be called a Monſter: but we will call it Sacriledge againſt God, the Lord and Author of Nature.</p>
               <p n="2">§ 2. That Honour and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61849:16"/>
which is the proper Act of Religion,<note place="margin">Ameſ. de Conſc. lib. <hi>4</hi> cap <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> is due only to God, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teacheth.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe it is the greateſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor that can be given to him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is the honor that is due to the ſole Lord of Life and Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Felicity.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Religious honour directly ſubmitteth, and ſubjecteth the ſoul and conſcience to the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</p>
               <p n="4">4 In Religious honour God only is acknowledged to be our ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Lord, and to have abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute right to require our Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
               <p>Thus Nature teaching us that every Religious Act is due unto God; then Parochial Church-Communion, being a Religious Act, is a Natural or Moral Duty commanded by the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Now Moral or Perpetual (relating to a Law) ſignifies (in the Notation of the word) any Precept ſerving to regulate the Manners of men.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sabbatum Redivivum part <hi>1.</hi> pag. <hi>9</hi>
                  </note>There are two kinds of Moral Lawes,; Moral-Natural, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal-Poſitive: which agreeing in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61849:16"/>
Perpetuity, do differ in their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Properties, as may appear by their ſeveral deſcriptions; which are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1 A Law Moral-Natural, is a Law of things neceſſary to be done or forborn toward God or Man, our ſelves or others; which the nature of man now (though corrupt) ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth acknowledge or may at leaſt be convinced of to be ſuch (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven without Scripture) by Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments drawn from thoſe Principles, which are now in the hearts of all men generally.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Lawes Moral-Poſitive, are Lawes clearly laid down in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (in words expreſſe,<note place="margin">Naturae majeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem recogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare, nulli frivolum videre po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. <hi>Tertul. de Teſtim. Animae. c. 5.</hi>
                  </note> or certain conſequence) which Nature, though corrupted, cannot reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably deny to be Juſt, Good, and ſo convenient to be perpetuated, according to the Law-givers plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: though antecedent to his will, ſome way revealed to them, it would not, nor could have judged them to be of themſelves altogether neceſſary.</p>
               <p>The diſtinction of Moral Laws into Natural and Poſitive being clear in their deſcriptions, their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61849:17"/>
is manifeſt in two things, beſides perpetuity.</p>
               <p n="1">1 In their Authority and force of Obligation; a Poſitive Law in force doth as ſtrongly bind the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as a Natural; <hi>aequè,</hi> though not <hi>aequaliter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 In their independance, both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon God, and not upon the will of man; and ſo are indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable by humane Authority. Theſe things premiſed, I conclude, that as all Solemn and Religious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God is Natural-Moral, ſo Parochial Church-Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is a Duty implanted by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p n="3">§. 3. But leſt I ſhould be thought to neglect (in effect) any other Solemn Worſhip, beſide this pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip in Church-Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; (which the Ancients in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereſt manner did preſcribe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire) I will briefly declare,<note place="margin">Concil. Gangren. cap. <hi>5.</hi> &amp; <hi>6</hi>
                  </note> that all Solemne Worſhip is Moral-Natural, in all the parts thereof; and ſo, by conſequence, this Worſhip in Church-Communion. Though the nature of man be much defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the Fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> yet are there (as all men do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg)
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61849:17"/>
ſome Principles of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on found in every ſoul, which can never be blotted out: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong which there are theſe two moſt legibly upon the Tables of the heart.</p>
               <p n="1">1 That there is a God: which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the moſt barbarous people in all ages, and the worſt of Atheiſts have beene forced to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That this God muſt be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped by all reaſonable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20</note> capable of his divine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg. This is that natural Homage and Alegeance due to God from all mankind, by the very law of Nature in their Creation;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are bound to perform all Duties that he preſcribes to them, both with ſoul and body. Our life then regulated by nature, is the honour of nature; but things done againſt Nature do hinder the Solemn Worſhip of God,<note place="margin">Euſeb. Orat ad Caet. Sanct. c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> ſaid <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great.</p>
               <p n="4">§ 4 The Worſhip of God may be diſtinguiſhed into Ejaculatory and Solemn. Ejaculatory Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is that which a man may ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der unto God, either with the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61849:18"/>
Heart alone, or with the Tongue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, in Prayer and Praiſes, even in the midſt of worldly imployments. To this kind of Worſhip every one is undoubtedly bound, as much as it is poſſible for us to perform it; and that, by thoſe general precepts which bind <hi>Semper,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 62.8 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.16 17, 18</note> (as the Schools ſpeak) that is, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n all opportunities; though not, <hi>ad ſemper,</hi> at all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, without intermiſſion. But indeed it is both our ſin and our miſery, that in our ordinary Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings we ſeldom remember God, as we might and ſhould: it being too true of all in a degree, To for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal</hi> 10.4</note> and not to have him in our thoughts. Solemn Worſhip is the preſenting the whole man, ſoul and body together unto God. Now this Solemn Worſhip, is diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into ſolitary, and conjoyn'd wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; which uſually, though not properly, is expreſſed by the terms of Private and Publick Worſhip; but we had rather call it Solitary, or Conjoyned, becauſe it is preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to God, either by any one ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular perſon alone, or by divers joyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing together in the tendring of it.</p>
               <p>That Solitary Worſhip is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61849:18"/>
Duty,<note place="margin">Sabbat. Red part <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> Sect. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> appeares from the grounds of Nature.</p>
               <p n="1">1 It is altogether unreaſonable to imagine that God ſhould loſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his honour from any man ſingle, becauſe there is none other company to joine with him in the Solemnity of Worſhip.</p>
               <p n="2">2 It is likewiſe unreaſonable to think, that a man is not bound to ſeek the recovery of his ſouls loſt happineſs, in his enjoying God indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Worſhip, becauſe he is alone.</p>
               <p>Next, Solemn Conjoyned Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, is Domeſtical or Eccleſiaſtical.</p>
               <p>That the Lord requires Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Worſhip from all ſuch jointly as live in Families, appears to be Moral-Natural, becauſe it being the Lord that hath placed men in a Community, it cannot be juſtly conceived, that he ſhould do this meerly for their worldly conveniences; but rather chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they ſhould improve their Society one with another to his Glory,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.6 <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.12 <hi>Eſth.</hi> 4.16 <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.3</note> who is the Lord of them altogether, as well as of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of them ſingle; and ſo that they ſhould worſhip him jointly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether as wel as each of them apart.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:61849:19"/>§ 5 Now all Eccleſiaſtical Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is ſo aſſuredly of the Law of Nature, that all Nations, that have ever been heard of, have had their joynt Publick Solemn Worſhip; and have had Perſons ſet apart pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely for it. No man denyeth this, for no man is ignorant of that which nature freely doth ſuggeſt,<note place="margin">Tertul. de Spectac. c. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> ſaith <hi>Tertullian.</hi> Moreover, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Experience declare, that the good of ſouls calls for Solemn Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Worſhip, and commends it, as abſolutely neceſſary and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable: not only in that men are hereby yet more affected by a more general example,<note place="margin">Sabbat. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>div. part <hi>1</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> Sect. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> recommending the Worſhip of God; but alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by the ſolemn Ordinances of Prayer, Preaching, Sacraments, Sabbaths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> multitudes are at once taught, minded of, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked to many Duties they owe to God and Man, better then their owne ſolitary thoughts or endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours could ordinarily have attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to. And this ſo much the rather, becauſe of the gifts, which God to this purpoſe hath endued his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters with (who by his appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are ſet apart mainly for the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61849:19"/>
Publick Worſhip) exceeding thoſe which others have uſually or ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily: yet by the advantage of Publick Worſhip every particular perſon preſent enjoyes the benefit of the Miniſters gifts,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.23.</note> for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification and Conſolation of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one, from whom it is not hid; and ſo may reap in one hour the ſtrength of that which hath been growing divers years, and feed upon that which hath beene gathering many dayes. This Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick Worſhip is ſo natural to man, that <hi>Tertullian</hi> wondreth,<note place="margin">Tert. de Cor Milit. cap. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> How any man can ask for Gods Law, ſeeing it is written openly in the Creatures, and naturally in the Tables of Hearts, unto which the Apoſtle doth appeal, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1.26, 27.</p>
               <p n="6">§. 6. This Eccleſiaſtical Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, is either determined or inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined.</p>
               <p>That thing is ſaid to be Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, which hath bounds and limits preſcribed. <hi>Determinare,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.14 <hi>Job</hi> 14.13.</note> 
                  <hi>eſt terminos conſtituere,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As that Worſhip then may be ſaid to be Determined, which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61849:20"/>
is limited with certaine Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, and circumſcribed: ſo that may be ſaid to be indetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whoſe Adminiſtration and Performance, is Caſual, Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal,<note place="margin">Ariſt. Eth. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> Accidental. The Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher telleth us, That Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances are the particular Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſingular Acts. Now cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances are determined in Scripture but in general, and left to Humane determination <hi>in ſpecie.</hi> Therefore <hi>Aquinas</hi> concludeth, That the conſideration of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin.</hi> 12.7, 2.0. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.18.3.0.</note> doth chiefly belong unto Divines; and that they make any Action either good or bad. And <hi>Scotus</hi> teacheth,<note place="margin">Scot. Sent. l. <hi>1.</hi> d. <hi>28</hi> quaeſ <hi>4.</hi> n. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> That the Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of a thing is twofold (oppoſite unto a twofold Indeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination) namely, a Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto Contradictories, or Poſitive Diverſities: and thence concludeth, that <hi>Determinatio ad alteram partem Contradictionis ſtat cum indeterminatione ad diverſa.</hi> And therefore the determination of Solemn Worſhip to Parochial Church-communion on the Lords Day, doth conſiſt with his Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined Worſhip at other times
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:61849:20"/>
and places on certaine occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>The ſum of all is, That Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and Parochial Church-Communion, is a Duty im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted by Nature, otherwiſe it were not abſolutely a Moral-Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Duty to worſhip God ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at all; for every ſuch Duty, which we by the Law of Nature owe unto God, cannot but be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually and univerſally poſſible to all; he being perpetually exiſtent and preſent with us, and we with him. And ſo by the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it is ſacriledg againſt God, to ſeparate from determined Church-Communion, chiefly without cauſe. But I paſs from Nature to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:61849:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> All Chriſtians are to joyne themſelves to ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular viſible Church, when the Lord offereth Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</head>
               <p n="1">§ 1. MY ſecond ſort or kind of Reaſoning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Practice I oppoſe, is deduced from plaine Scripture. And here, though I might plead, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> did,<note place="margin">Tert. de Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nogam. c. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Scriptura negat, quod non notat;</hi> That the Scripture deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that which it teacheth not: And ſeeing this practice hath no Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture-warrant (for any thing that I ever yet ſaw or heard) the Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of it ſhould fear that Woe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, not only againſt them that adde or diminiſh, but likewiſe that adulterate the ſenſe of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.<note place="margin">Tertull. de Praeſcr. c. <hi>17</hi>
                  </note> For according to <hi>Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> Rule, the Scripture is as much
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:61849:21"/>
wronged by perverting the ſenſe, as by corrupting the words of it. But to deal with them with their own weapons: Where is it ſaid, That you are not to joyne in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined Church Communion, to hear your own Paſtor? Where are thoſe words written? If they anſwer, Negatives cannot be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, To this we reply, And where is that ſaid? for we find it no where in Scripture,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.39. <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.7</note> that Negatives cannot be proved. Yea, we find that Chriſt proved Negatives; for he proved, that himſelf was not a Spirit, That God was not to be tempted, &amp;c. If Negatives are not to be proved, then Negatives are not to be belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Ours is an Affirmative,<note place="margin">Hooker Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Politic. l. <hi>2.</hi> Sect. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> which they yeild may be proved; theirs is a Negative, which they ſay cannot be proved: We then have the better of it; there is hope of proof on our ſide; theirs is deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate. But though I might deſire them to prove their Practice by Scripture, yet becauſe with <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Contra Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mog. c. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> I adore the fulneſſe of the Scripture, I will ſhew their practiſe, who on the Lords Day neglect the publick exerciſes of Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61849:22"/>
in their determined Parochial Congregations, and frequent <hi>(cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris paribus)</hi> other Churches, to be Anti-ſcriptural. Thus:</p>
               <p n="2">§ 2. Firſt, all are to joyn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to a viſible Church; either Formally to be a member thereof, or Materially by confeſſing the Faith of the true viſible Church, when God offereth occaſion.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Becauſe we ought to be ready to give an anſwer or confeſſion to every one that asketh, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Becauſe <hi>he who denyeth Chriſt before men, him alſo will Chriſt deny before his Father, and the holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> Mat. 10.33.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Becauſe Chriſt hath promiſed his preſence to his Churches, as he <hi>walked in the midſt of the golden candleſticks,</hi> Rev. 2.1.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Becauſe Faith cometh by hearing a ſent Preacher, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.24.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Becauſe ſeparation from a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church is condemned, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.24. <hi>Jude</hi> 19. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.19.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Becauſe the godly ever eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it a rich favor of God, to lay
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61849:22"/>
hold on the skirt of a Jew; that is, to have any communion,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zech.</hi> 8.3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.4. <hi>et</hi> 42.1. <hi>&amp;c et</hi> 63.1, 2.</note> even as a door-keeper in the Houſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God, and have deſired it exceedingly, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of the want thereof, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.1, 2, 10.</p>
               <p n="3">§ 3 Yet if any die without the Church, having faith in Chriſt, and want opportunity to confeſſe him before men, as repenting at the hour of death, their ſalvation is ſure, becauſe they are within the Church. So is that Maxime to be taken,<note place="margin">Cam. de Ecc. p. <hi>272.</hi> in ſol</note> 
                  <hi>Extra Eccleſiam non eſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las;</hi> None can be ſaved who are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way without tho Church, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and Inviſible; as all periſhed who were not in <hi>Noahs</hi> Ark.<note place="margin">Mr. Blake Cov. cap. <hi>30</hi> in ſinc.</note> As for thoſe who deny any being of a Church univerſal viſible, I would learn of them into what particular Church the Eunuch was received, and by Baptiſm actually and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly admitted; or whether he was ſtill no Church-member, but an alien and ſtranger to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> not admitted to the Church? And to what par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Congregation the Prophets, Apoſtles and Evangeliſts joyned
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:61849:23"/>
themſelves by Covenant?</p>
               <p n="4">§ 4 There is then a neceſſity of joyning our ſelves to ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular viſible Church; but it is not <hi>Neceſſitas medii, ſed praecepti;</hi> It is not ſuch a neceſſity that all are damned who are not within ſome viſible Church.<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> For <hi>Auguſtine</hi> tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaith, <hi>There be many Wolves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Church, and many Sheep with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out.</hi> But if the Lord offer oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, all are obliged by his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of confeſſing Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, to joyn themſelvs to ſome Viſible-church: for all Denying, is Idolatry,<note place="margin">Tert. de I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolol. c. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> in <hi>Tertullians</hi> judgment. And he denyeth Chriſt, that is not with him, or for him. So our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour teacheth, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.23. <hi>He that is not with me, is againſt me; and he that gathereth not with me, ſcattereth;</hi> that is, He that declareth not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be on my ſide, is againſt me. There are no Neuters; for there is no man but he is either Chriſts or Satans.<note place="margin">Eng. Annot on Mat. <hi>12.30.</hi>
                  </note> As in war, he that ſight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not for his Prince is an enemy. As they which are to gather in their Maſters harveſt, if they neglect it, are ſcatterers and deſtroyers; ſo they that will not defend Chriſts
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:61849:23"/>
honor, at leaſt profeſſe and confeſſe it (wherein they can) betray his cauſe, and are enemies. Yet there is a fellowſhip with the viſible church internal, of hidden Believers. In the <hi>Romiſh Babel</hi> this is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for ſalvation, <hi>Neceſſitate medii.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rutherford Due Right of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery. c. <hi>5.</hi> Sect <hi>5.</hi> p. <hi>78</hi>
                  </note> But they want opportunity to joyne themſelves to the reformed viſible churches; yet do they ſin in the want of profeſſion of the Truth, and in not witneſſing againſt the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt; which is anſwerable to an adjoyning themſelves to a viſible church. And ſo thoſe who do not profeſs the faith of the true viſible church (the Lord affording oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity) deny Chriſt before men. And this external fellowſhip is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to all, <hi>Neceſſitate Praecepti:</hi> though the Lord graciouſly pardon this, as an infirmity in his own, who for fear of cruel perſecution, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten dare not confeſſe Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:61849:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> We are bound to Hearing in our own determined Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, <hi>Neceſſitate Praecepti.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">§ 1. SEcondly, Howſoever we be not bound unto hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in our own Congregations, <hi>Neceſſitate Medii,</hi> as if Gods grace were tyed to the Meanes this way: Yet <hi>Neceſſitate Praecepti,</hi> we are, if we conſider Gods Commandment: In no other way can we expect the Lords ordinary preſence, promiſe, and acceptance: See <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.12. It is a curſe, to be as <hi>Sheep having no ſhepherd,</hi> Matth. 9.36. that is, ſcattered abroad, not knowing where to get food, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to many Seducers,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.176 <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.17. <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.7</note> as people without a Paſtor. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a Scattering enforc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> men are driven by viol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:61849:24"/>
Gods ſervice, but that is not the ſcattering meant by our Saviour; but a voluntary ſtraying, when people are not willing only, but love to wander; as <hi>Jer.</hi> 14.10. a wandring out of ſelf-will; not a corporal, but a ſpiritual ſtraying, by which men of themſelves wander from God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58.3</note> and go aſtray from the way of Truth and Life; from thoſe wayes and courſes that God hath preſcribed them in his Word, and directed them unto by his Spirit: as they, Pſal. 14.3.</p>
               <p n="2">§ 2. It is the Duty of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious Chriſtians to ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under ſome particular Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter as their Paſtor, and to hear him conſtantly.<note place="margin">Ameſ. de Conſc. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>24.</hi> quaeſ. <hi>1</hi>
                  </note> Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> proves that this Ordinance of the Lord is the Duty of all Chriſtians; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to ſettle themſelves under ſome one particular Paſtor, and to joyne themſelvs to a determined or parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Becauſe it is Chriſts inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.17. in which there is a neceſſity, <hi>Non Praecepti tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ſed &amp; Medii:</hi> He addeth five Reaſons more, which for brovitice ſake I omit.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:61849:25"/>2. Becauſe every Flock muſt be under an Overſeer, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. &amp; 18.23. If we be the flock of Chriſt, we muſt have a ſhepherd, who ſhall feed us in Chriſts ſtead.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Becauſe our perfection and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification dependeth ordinarily up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our particular Teacher, to which end Paſtors were given, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11, 12. and particular Guides, as <hi>Philip</hi> to the Eunuch.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Becauſe Paſtors are to preach conſtantly, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4, 2. eſpecially on the Lords Day they ſhould not omit to preach Forenoon and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon.<note place="margin">Ameſ. de Conſc. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>33.</hi> quaeſt. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> notes, that to the Sanctification of that Day, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of publick Worſhip in a Church, well conſtituted, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying her Liberty, ought to bee held forth forenoon and afternoon. Halfe the Lords Day ſpent in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion will not ſuffice to diſcharge from the ſecond due attendance on that Day:<note place="margin">Sabb. Red. part <hi>1</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi> Sect. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> For if the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture determine for every worky-day of mans life, at leaſt a double atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon God, as neceſſary unto all men, much more on the Lords day. The continuance being not
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:61849:25"/>
here determined, the ſervice may be ſo ſuddenly diſpatched, as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but want of will and Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can be aſſigned, as the cauſe of not tendring that double pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion on the moſt buſie day, that any man hath in his whole life.</p>
               <p n="3">§ 3. Furthermore, reverend Mr. <hi>Collings</hi> proves by four Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments,<note place="margin">Vindiciae Miniſt. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vang. quaeſt. <hi>5.</hi> p. <hi>82.</hi>
                  </note> that it is the duty of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Chriſtians, who have ſet themſelves under particular Paſtors, not to neglect them when they do preach. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. To what purpoſe made they choice of him?</p>
               <p n="2">2. He hath a particular over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight over them committed to him, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.12 <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.17, 14.</p>
               <p n="3">3 A Paſtors more eſpecial tye to his own Flock then another, (<hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2.) argues that they are more eſpecially tied to him, and that he is appointed to feed them.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Chriſtians own Paſtors have a more ſpecial diſpenſation of the grace of God given them to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.2. Of which more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:61849:26"/>Now then, lay theſe together; Is it the duty of private Chriſtians, who have ſet themſelvs under their particular Paſtors, to attend divine Ordinances on the Lords day, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered forenoon and afternoon? But ſee the times,<note place="margin">Dr. Harrie, Peters En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largm. in Prefat.</note> Reader! It is la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable to conſider the little uſe that is made of Gods Ordinances in moſt places; Preachers too often (I tremble to ſpeak it, or write it) be uſed like Poſt-horſes, ſpurred on till they be ſpent, and then a freſh is called for; in the mean time the world ſits ſtil, and thinks to be ſaved for hearing. Reader, mourn for this, weep for this; for this boads a Judgment; the Lord will ſurely reckon for the blood of his ſervants, ſpent,<note place="margin">Nazian. ad Baſ.</note> as well as ſhed. See <hi>Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anzen</hi> his complaint, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 31.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:61849:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> God aſſigneth unto every or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Paſtor a portion of his people, to be instructed by him.</head>
               <p n="1">§ 1. THirdly,<note place="margin">Rav. in voce <hi>Gratia.</hi> num. <hi>3.</hi> diſt. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> A Miniſters Calling is termed in Scripture, <hi>The Grace of God;</hi> as <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.2. And it is ſo termed in a twofold reſpect:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe the deſigning to the Miniſterial Calling is of grace.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And the faculty qualifying us for it, is from the free favour of God.</p>
               <p>The Miniſterial Function then hath theſe two properties:</p>
               <p n="1">1 It is founded in the free pleaſure of God, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.15.</p>
               <p n="2">2. All the ſufficiency which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableth any man to diſpence the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the Goſpel, it is the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61849:27"/>
meer grace of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10. From theſe premiſſes I infer, That as God giveth Miniſters their Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ſo alſo their people, toward whom he will bleſſe their labours. It is true, the care of all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches was laid on the Apoſtle;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28</note> but not ſo now: for whereſoever God now giveth a Miniſterial Calling, there he giveth a people, of whom the Miniſter may ſay, Towards you grace is given me of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Bains ad locum.</note>This is Mr. <hi>Bains</hi> his obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.2. That Chriſtians own Paſtors have a more ſpecial diſpenſation of the grace of God given them to them-ward. Whence he concludeth; This ſhould inſtruct people to depend eſpecially on thoſe who are ſet over them, for thoſe are they who are furniſhed from God in an eminent manner with grace towards them: They are fooliſh Pigeons that know not their owne Lockers; and fooliſh ſheep that know not their ſhepherds voice; and fooliſh people that know not their Miniſter.</p>
               <p n="2">§ 2. Hence then it is evident, That God aſſigneth to every ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Miniſter a portion of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:61849:27"/>
This is the difference between Ordinary and Extraordinary Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors. For ordinary Miniſters, the Lord commanded to faſten them to certain places; <hi>Ordain Elders in every City,</hi> Tit. 1.5.<note place="margin">Conc. Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce. l. c. <hi>6.</hi> An. <hi>451.</hi> Epau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen. c. <hi>2.</hi> An. <hi>515.</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt. c. <hi>22.</hi> An. <hi>829.</hi> Tribur. c. <hi>27</hi> An. <hi>895.</hi>
                  </note> And in the Councel of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> it is decreed, <hi>Nemo ordinetur abſolutè;</hi> Let none be Ordained at large, leſt he prove a wandring <hi>Jonathan. Caranza</hi> addeth three other Councels, that decreed a wandring Levite not to be admitted into communion: the reaſon is rendred by the Canoniſts, <hi>Ne dicatur, Mendicat in palaeſtra in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felix Clericus.</hi> Every Miniſter then muſt be ſeparated, authorized, and have allotted to him a certaine portion of people, which may bee inſtructed by him: which the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minutive <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, may ſeem to inſinuate in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. Now as God giveth to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Paſtor his ſeveral Flock, ſo he will that we take pains in lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them. We muſt not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, be Biſhops in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens Dioceſſes, leſt God ſay, Who requireth this at your hand? When the Lord lighteth Candles, he findeth candleſticks on which
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:61849:28"/>
to ſet them; and when hee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth a Calling, he giveth a people amongſt whom this Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſhould be exerciſed, in whoſe conſciences (unleſſe they be ſcared) he giveth his Miniſter a peculiar re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port.</p>
               <p n="3">§ 3. Indeed if any come to our Congregations, as wanting their ſpiritual food by the Word and Sacraments, then it is good for a Miniſter to bee like a young woman (ſaith Mr. <hi>Bains</hi>) ſo full breſted that ſhee can both feed her owne child fat,<note place="margin">Bains ubi ſupra.</note> and lend a draught to her neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.<note place="margin">Ruther. Due Right of Presbyt. c. <hi>4.</hi> Sect. <hi>5.</hi> p. <hi>185</hi>
                  </note> Eſpecially the Seales of the Covenant are not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed to approved Profeſſors of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Congregation: for wee hold, all who profeſſe the Faith of Chriſt to be Members of the Viſible Church, though they bee not members of a viſible con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation; and that the Seals of the Covenant ſhould not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed them. But to let an itch of vain glory carry us ſo far, as to affect this that cometh from without, and be cold at home; this is to forget where our grace
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:61849:28"/>
principally lyeth. Miniſters are Stars, and the beſt ſhine is in our own Sphere. This I ſay not, as if it were not lawful in ſome caſes, to lend our labour elſewhere. For (due circumſtances conſidered) we may ſay as he,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 16.9</note> 
                  <hi>Come help us in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonia.</hi> And it was a cuſtome in the Primitive times (as <hi>Clemens</hi> teſtifieth) that if any Presbyter or Biſhop came to another,<note place="margin">Conſtit. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>48.</hi>
                  </note> they ſhall be entreated to preach, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it falleth out, as Chriſt ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.57</note> 
                  <hi>A Prophet is not without ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, ſave in his own Country, and in his own houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Paſtors then do warrantably performe Paſtoral Acts in other Congregations beſide their own:<note place="margin">Mr. Ruther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford ubi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra. p. <hi>204.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 Becauſe wee hold, that by Calling or Ordination, a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is made a Paſtor; by Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction only he is reſtrained to be ordinarily the Paſtor of his Flock.</p>
               <p n="2">2 A Paſtor is a Paſtor of the Catholick Church, though he be not a Catholick Paſtor of the Catholick Church, as were the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:61849:29"/>§ 4. Neither muſt this be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as if we would clack you (as reverend <hi>Bains</hi> phraſeth it) altogether under our wings, or ſought further property, then we have from the Lord; but it is your good that doth enforce us to ſpeak it; for till you know your Paſtors ſet over you, the Wolfe doth threaten you. And look, that as it is in Marriage: it is not the having of a husband, which maketh a wife free from all underminers of chaſtity, but the loving her husband: So in this Marriage of Paſtor and People; it is not the having of a Preacher, which doth ſecure you from ſin, ſatan, or ſeduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but the acknowledging of him, and depending on him in the Lord. So much did the Heathen by the light of Nature reverence their Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties of old, the Slaves of their Idol Gods, that ſometimes they called their Prieſts by the name of Gods,<note place="margin">Strabo Geogr. l. <hi>10</hi> p. <hi>471</hi> d.</note> as <hi>Strabo</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth. And among Chriſtians, I never read nor heard of an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:61849:29"/>
Church without a good Guide, and a dependance on him, and obedience to him. It is a farre leſſe ſin to be unlearned then unteachable, ſaith <hi>Aguſtine.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Academ lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> O be taught then, not to depart from your determined place of worſhipping the Lord; for in it, God hath the higheſt honour, and returnes unto you the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt bleſſings, by the diſpenſation of the grace of God, which is given your Paſtor to you-ward.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.2.</note> Be not wilful: for the more wilful, eſpecially upon deliberation, the more wicked.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:61849:30"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Separation from determined Church-Communion, is reproved, <hi>1 Cor. 1.12. and 3.4.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">§ 1. FOurthly, This pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice is evidently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. For in the church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> which <hi>Paul</hi> had planted, <hi>Apollos</hi> had watered, and which God had bleſſed, and given encreaſe unto; yet even here is church-ſeparation. One ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for <hi>Paul,</hi> another for <hi>Apollos,</hi> another for <hi>Cephas.</hi> Weeds, they will ſpring up, though <hi>Paul</hi> never planted them, nor <hi>Apollos</hi> watered them, to be ſure God never bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them; and yet they will find an encreaſe. And 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.4. the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle tacitely inſinuates an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>à Minori ad Majus:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Culverw. of Schiſme.</note> If it
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:61849:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
were a groſſe and carnal thing to ſide with <hi>Paul,</hi> or to glory in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollos,</hi> then much more to ſide with ſuch as of ordinary or inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or alloy. You may ſee how he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to beat down this over-high thought which they had of ſuch as indeed deſerved e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem and double honour. For to ſay, <hi>I am of Paul, I am of Apollos,</hi> they are the words of ſuch as glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſeveral gifts and diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of excellencies which they had in preaching the Goſpel: and thus it was, one liketh the powerful plaineſſe of <hi>Paul,</hi> another the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple plenty and variety of <hi>Apollos,</hi> a third the ſolidity and perſpicuity of <hi>Cephas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">§ 2. You ſee then the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians vanity, and in it our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſity to glory in men for their gifts, and that becauſe we are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, which is the Apoſtles cenſure, painted with a ſtinging Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Are ye not carnal?</hi> In ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.13. giveth three Reaſons why ſuch church-ſeparation ſhould be ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Becauſe Chriſt ſeemeth by
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:61849:31"/>
that means to be divided and torn in pieces,<note place="margin">Eng. Ann. in loc.</note> who cannot be the head of two diverſe and diſagreeing bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, himſelf being but one. <hi>Is Chriſt divided?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 Becauſe they cannot without injury to God, ſo depend on men, as on Chriſt; which thing, no doubt they do, who allow whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſome man ſpeaketh, even for his perſon ſake; approving one ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame Goſpel, being uttered by one man, and diſliking it being ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by another man; <hi>Was Paul crucified for you?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 Becauſe it is the form and end of Baptiſm to make a promiſe to Chriſt alone, calling on alſo the Name of the Father and the Holy Ghoſt; therefore if a man depend on ſome certain Teachers, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe others, he forſaketh Chriſt: for if he held Chriſt his only Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, he would hear him teaching by whomſoever: <hi>Were ye baptized in the name of Paul?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">§ 3 Overmuch dotage then upon any conceived excellency of Holineſſe, Learning, Eloquence, or the like, without a ſpecial eye to Gods commandment, hath ever
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:61849:31"/>
been the occaſion of greateſt Errors in the world.<note place="margin">Mr. Mede on Gen. <hi>3.13</hi>
                  </note> Satan under this mask uſeth to blear our eyes, and with this bait to inveigle our hearts, that hee might ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely bring us to his lure.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.1.</note> It was the mask of the Serpents Wiſdome and Sagacity above the reſt of the beaſts of the field, whereby he brought to paſſe our firſt parents ruine. The admirable wiſdome of the long lived Fathers of the elder world, having been for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ages as Oracles to their Off-ſpring, growne even to a People and Nation while they yet lived, was the ground of the ancient Idolatry of Mankind, whilſt they ſuppoſed that thoſe, to whom for wiſedome they had recourſe, being living, could not but help them being dead. This we may learn out of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiod:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heſiod. Oper &amp; Dic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ver. <hi>123.</hi>
                  </note> The men (ſaith he) of the golden age, being once dead, became,
<q>
                     <l>— <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:61849:32"/>
They became Godlings and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons of mortal men, as if they knew their good and evil works. So the opinion of the bleſſed Martyrs ſuperlative glory in heaven, was made the occaſion of the new found Idolatry of Chriſtians, wherewith they are for the greater part yet over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed. And the eſteeme which <hi>Peter</hi> had above the reſt of the Apoſtles in regard of Chiefdome, even in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles times, was abuſed by the old Deceiver to inſtall the Man of ſin. This made Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to ſay, <hi>The Myſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity was even then working:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.11. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> and therefore laboured, as fat as he could to prevent it, by as much depreſſing <hi>Peter,</hi> as others exalted him. Nay, he puts us all in mind of the ſtory of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents beguiling <hi>Eve,</hi> that her miſ-hap might be a warning to all, 2 <hi>Corinth</hi> 11.2, 3.</p>
               <p>And to conclude, Have not Papiſts, when they would get Diſciples, learned this of the Divel, to poſſeſſe them firſt with an opinion of ſuperlative
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:61849:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Learning, Holineſſe, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gifts, in their Doctors, ſurpaſſing any of ours? I will ſay no more of this, but that we ought ſo to prize and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the Gifts and Abilities, which God hath beſtowed upon men, that the Pole-Star of his ſacred Word may ever be in our eye.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> The Lord commandeth to worſhip him orderly: which is not obſerved in indermined Church-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</head>
               <p n="1">§ 1. FIfthly, Order is a thing ſo highly pleaſing the Lord, as the three Perſons in the bleſſed Trinity have put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Order, to ſhew how well they love it: And order is a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:61849:33"/>
thing ſo neerly concerning us,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7. <hi>Zech.</hi> 10.7</note> as break Order once, and break both your Staves (ſaith God in <hi>Zachary</hi>) both that of Beauty, and that of Bands. The Staffe of Beauty; for no <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, no manner of decency or comelineſs without it, but all out of faſhion. The ſtaffe of Bands; for no <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, no kind of Steadineſſe or conſtancy, but all looſe without it:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.2. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> All falls back to the firſt <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hu</hi> and <hi>Bohu;</hi> for all is <hi>Toha</hi> (empty and void) if God fill not in Order; all is <hi>Bohu,</hi> a diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered rude chaos of confuſion, if Chriſt order it not. Every body falls to be doing with every thing, and ſo nothing done; nothing well done, I am ſure. Every man then ſhould, whatever his Gifts be, order his Place and Standing in Divine Worſhip by Chriſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned him. This is judged need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful even in ſecular matters. Write one never ſo fair an hand, if hee have not Orderly the Calling of a publick Notary, his Writing is not authentical: Be one never ſo good a Lawyer, if he be not order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be a Judge, he can give no
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:61849:33"/>
definitive Sentence.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Scot. l.</hi> 2. <hi>Sent. d.</hi> 2. <hi>q.</hi> 12. <hi>n.</hi> 3. <hi>Aquin.</hi> 22.26.1.0.</note> The Order of Nature is prefixed by God, and is neceſſarily to be obſerved by every Natural cauſe, ſaith one School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: And whereſoever there is a beginning, there muſt be ſome Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſaith another.</p>
               <p n="2">§ 2. Ignorance of the Truth, as <hi>Lactantius</hi> noteth well, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <hi>incertam labentemque ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam,</hi> an uncertain and ſlippery aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion. Will-Worſhip is no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Act, becauſe it is not direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Divine Order. Neither are good Intentions enough.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 4.23</note> We muſt be certain of Gods revealed will to order us in his Worſhip, otherwiſe we cannot do it in faith. Now this is Will-Worſhip, to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing anſwer for Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, to our ſelves, of our ſelves, without Order from God, and warrant of his Word.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Amos</hi> 5.26. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.22. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.16</note> We muſt be Paſsive, not Active here. Mans Deviſe and Self-wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome at the beſt, pretend what he will, is no warrant for Gods Worſhip; eſpecially Amphibo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, Equivocations, Mental Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, or the like: for how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they may ſilence the cry of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:61849:34"/>
a carnal conſcience, yet they are but ſhifts and ſhuffles, which have no ground from Gods Word. Though <hi>Iſrael</hi> had builded Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.14.</note> to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of God, yet the Lord calls it, a forgetting of him their Maker. God will be worſhipped onely by the rule of his Word. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the dignity of <hi>Adams</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent condition in Innocency, the variety and plenty of proviſion he had without any coſt or paines of his own, he was not to live an i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle life, and without order. And though he were to work on the Week dayes without ſweat or wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſſe, yet on the Sabbath (by Gods example, if not by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand) he was to reſt from that work, to give himſelf more inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively to the Worſhip of God, and communion with God; which he could not ſo well do, if he did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing elſe at the ſame time. It is not then as <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">Lactan. l. <hi>3</hi> c. <hi>9</hi>
                  </note> (and our Atheiſts and Epicures do) Man was born to ſee the Sun, and look unto the Heavens; but to ſeek, know, and ſerve the Lord his Maſter. He not only giveth life,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:61849:34"/>
but means alſo, by which we may orderly, diſtinctly,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 17.27.</note> obſerving due cicumſtances, come to know him.</p>
               <p n="3">§. 3. A thing then may bee good in the ſubſtance, and yet in the Circumſtances (Time, Place, Perſon, &amp;c.) unwarrantable.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 12.3 <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.11</note> As the Iſraelites worſhipping in the High Places; the Duty was good, but the place where it was perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, was prohibited: ſo the Duty of Will-worſhip in the Indetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Service of God, in a Church enjoying her freedome, the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man telleth us,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin.</hi> 12.73.7.0.</note> That the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance aggravateth the Sin. In matters that concerne God, who is ſo fit to be conſulted with, as he whom God ſetteth over us, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daineth for the ſelf-ſame purpoſe? In the order of the Univerſe, not only is the Kind or Species intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but alſo the individuals in the principal parts thereof, ſaith <hi>Scotus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Scot. in Sent l.</hi> 2. <hi>d.</hi> 3. <hi>q.</hi> 7. <hi>ad</hi> 5. <hi>Aquin.</hi> 1.47.3.0, <hi>&amp;</hi> 1 106.3.2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> And all things created by God, have an order to God, and mutually to themſelves, ſaith <hi>Aquinas:</hi> His reaſon is, Becauſe all Order dependeth on the Will of God. Hence I infer, That oftentimes the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:61849:35"/>
circumſtance of an Action marrs the ſubſtance; and that in divine matters, we muſt not only look that the body of our ſervice be ſound, but that the cloathes be ſit. The Princes of the Philiſtines had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore given their voices what ſhould be done with the Ark of God,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.10</note> yet nothing is done without the direction and aſſent of thoſe whom they accounted Sacred. Nature it ſelf ſendeth us in divine things to thoſe perſons whoſe Calling is divine. It is either diſtruſt, or preſumption, or contempt that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries us our own wayes in ſpiritual matters, without adviſing with them, whoſe lips God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to preſerve knowledge. The Philiſtines deſired to be directed by their Prieſts and Diviners in the matter of their Oblation;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.4</note> 
                  <hi>What ſhall be the Treſpaſſe Offering</hi> (ſay they) <hi>which we ſhall return unto God?</hi> They knew well that it were bootleſſe for them to offer what they liſted. Pagans can teach us, how unſafe it is to walk in the wayes of Religion without a determined and certaine Guide. This is likewiſe confirmed by the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:61849:35"/>
cuſtom and Canons of the ancient Church: For it was decreed in the Councel at <hi>Eliberin,</hi> about the year 310.<note place="margin">Conc. Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. cap. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>That if any man (without a lawful cauſe) ſtayed three Lords Days from his Pariſh Church, his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was, that he ſhould be ſo long time excluded from Chriſtian Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies.</hi> Moreover <hi>Coriolanus</hi> citeth out of <hi>Burchard</hi> another Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of the ſame Councel, in which it was determined, <hi>That they who came ſeldom to their Pariſh Church, ſhould not at their approach to death, be admitted into Communion, before they brought forth fruits meet for repentance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">§ 4 In vain is comfort expected from God,<note place="margin">Be Hall, Contemp. <hi>81</hi>
                  </note> if we conſult not with his particular Vice-gerent, that hath overſight over us: For <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> in his diſtreſſe for <hi>Ziklag,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.7</note> ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> called for <hi>Abiather;</hi> he could not live in the Court of <hi>Achiſh</hi> a Heathen King, without his Seer and overſeer. Hence <hi>Gad</hi> is called <hi>Davids Seer,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.11.<note place="margin">Ravanel. in <hi>Videre.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Heman the Kings Secr,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 25.5. <hi>Jeduthun the Kings Seer,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 35.15. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they put their Kings princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:61849:36"/>
and particularly in mind of thoſe things which appertained to the ſervice and worſhip of the Lord. And if <hi>David</hi> a Prophet, a man after Gods own heart, had need of a particular Seer; ſhould not meane and ordinary Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans much more attend to the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and inſtructions of their particular Guides, allotted to them, and allowed by the Lord, who is the God of Order,<note place="margin">See Engliſh Annotat. in <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>14.40.</hi>
                  </note> and not the Authour of Confuſion; and hath commanded all things to be done decently and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:61849:36"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> We are bound to hearing in our particular Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by Chriſts Doctrine and Example.</head>
               <p n="1">§ 1. SIxthly, Gods covenant indeed is general with all his Creatures;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.9.18 <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.30</note> more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar with Man, yet more with his Church, moſt ſpecial with his Elect; and in his Church with his Miniſters, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.5 Now this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with Gods Miniſters and Meſſengers is everlaſting, in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and generations. Yet God, Covenant abrogates not his owne Right, Power and Soveraignty; nor abates the role and Authority of his Law, nor their deviations and corruptions; nay, his Curſe upon ſinful Prieſts and Paſtors doth not annihilate or evacuate that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:61849:37"/>
In regard of this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant it is,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.2.</note> that our Saviour intimates that all Teachers ſit in <hi>Moſes</hi> Seat, as Expounders of Gods Will, no leſſe then the Scribes and Phariſees.<note place="margin">Engl. Ann. in locum.</note> For <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> importeth the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a Teaching the Word of God, Law and Goſpel; becauſe while men taught, they were wont to ſit. <hi>Suidas</hi> therefore interpret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> by <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or tarrying; becauſe God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Teachers of the Law, therefore Chriſt would have them to be heard, though their Perſons were wicked. All whatſoever they bid you obſerve, that obſerve and do. While Paſtors have a Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to preach and deliver the Truth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.7</note> they muſt be heard, though not imitated, where they practiſe not.<note place="margin">Chryſ. Hom. <hi>73.</hi>
                  </note> Thus our Saviour ſpeaketh (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome) All whatſoever they bid you obſerve, that obſerve and do,</hi> leſt he ſhould leave the Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers any occaſion of Diſobedience, to their greater condemnation, or contempt of their Miniſtry whom he ſhould ſend after. In the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry the Ordinance of God is to be conſidered; <hi>Sive Paulus, ſive
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:61849:37"/>
Judas baptizet, Chriſtus peccatum lavat, abſolvit, &amp; delet.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Bapt. Chriſti. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter opera Cypr.</note> Whether <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Judas</hi> baptize, Chriſt waſheth away, forgiveth, and putteth away ſin. <hi>De Bapt. Chr. Cypr.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">§ 2 Our Saviour when he had cleanſed the ten Lepers, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to ſhew themſelves to the Prieſts, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.14. which ſhould teach us Humility and ſubjection toward our Paſtors,<note place="margin">Cypr. l. <hi>3</hi> Ep. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Sacerdotem adhuc appellabat, quem ſcicbat eſſe ſacrilegum:</hi> For Chriſt yet called him Prieſt, whom he knew to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious, ſaith <hi>Cyprian.</hi> Our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our likewiſe, who could as eaſily have taught <hi>Paul</hi> immediately what he would have him to do,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 9.10. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> would yet ſend him to <hi>Ananias (Ananias</hi> as ignorant of Gods will herein, as <hi>Saul</hi> at preſent, and ſtarting at, and declining the office enjoyned him) to cofirm the particular authority of the Miniſtry of particular men ſet over us in the Lord;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16</note> and to teach all Hearers to attend unto it, as the very Ordinance and power of God unto ſalvation. Chriſt could likewiſe, <hi>câdem operâ,</hi> have inſtructed the Centurion by the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:61849:38"/>
Angel;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 10.3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> but he cauſed him to ſend <hi>(nominatim)</hi> for <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Joppa,</hi> to come and enform him for the ſame end, and left him not to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of one at random.</p>
               <p n="3">§ 3. But here once for all, leſt we ſhould be miſunderſtood: We abhor the Doctrine of <hi>Bellarmine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bellarm. de Cleric. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> who teacheth, <hi>Cum Paſtor ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us &amp; aliquis alias qui praedicat non Vocatus, contraria docent, debet omnino populus Paſtorem ſuum potias ſequi, quam illum alterum qui non eſt Paſtor; etiamſi fortè continge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, ut Paſtor erraret:</hi> When an ordinary Paſtor and another who is not called to be a Paſtor, do teach things contrary, the people ought rather to follow their owne Paſtor then the other who is no Paſtor, though it fall out that the Paſtor do erre.</p>
               <p>In like manner we deteſt the Doctrine of <hi>Tolet</hi> the Jeſuite,<note place="margin">Tolet. de In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerd. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>3</hi> Sect. <hi>6</hi>
                  </note> who ſaith, <hi>Si Ruſticus citra articulos cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat ſuo Epiſcopo proponenti aliquod Dogma Haereticum, meretur creden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, licet ſit error:</hi> If a Countrey man, beſide Chriſtian Articles, do believe his Biſhop broaching an
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:61849:38"/>
Hereſie, he meriteth by believing, though it be an Error.</p>
               <p>Furthermore,<note place="margin">Bellarm. de Rom. Pont. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>5</hi>
                  </note> it is a fearful Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> teacheth, <hi>Si autem Papa erraret praecipiendo vitia, vel prohibendo virtutes, tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur Eccleſia credere vitia eſſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, &amp; virtutes malas:</hi> If the Pope ſhould erre by commanding Vices, and forbidding Vertues, the Church were bound to believe, that Vices were good, and Vertues evil.</p>
               <p>And we condemn the intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble preſumption of the Councel of <hi>Trent,</hi> that ſealeth up their Canons with ſo many <hi>Anathema's</hi> to them who diſſent from their Errors. Yet not onely did their Schoolman, <hi>William of Occam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Occam part <hi>1.</hi> l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>28.</hi>
                  </note> each the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in effect to all theſe, <hi>Si Papa &amp; maximè celebres Epiſcopi inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in Haereſin, ad Catholicos divo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luta eſt poteſtas omnis judicandi;</hi> if the Pope and the principal Biſhops of the Chriſtian world do fall into Hereſie, the power of all Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical judgment is divolved to the remaining Catholick Clergy: but alſo <hi>Cyprian, Cecili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cypr. Ep. <hi>68</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lycarpus,</hi> and others, writing
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:61849:39"/>
to the Clergy in <hi>Spain,</hi> perſwade them to ſeparate themſelves from thoſe Biſhops who fell in time of perſecution, and denyed the Faith.</p>
               <p n="4">§ 4. Now, it is much to be admired, that it ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed in <hi>Theſi,</hi> but denyed by the world in <hi>Hypotheſi,</hi> that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever oppoſeth, deſpiſeth, or perſecuteth the ſervants of Chriſt, they riſe up to oppoſe Chriſt himſelfe.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 10.16 <hi>Acts</hi> 9.4 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.8</note> What hath the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular oppoſed Paſtor done contrary to the general confeſſed Theſis or Divine Poſition? What hath he aſſumed what the Lord hath not put upon him? If ye take offence at the diſcharge of his Office, it is Gods doing, who fearfully and frequently threatneth his neglect. But men think they are not ſo ſilly and unreaſonable as their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter would make them. God doth not reveal his Truth (ſay they) onely or chiefly to the Learned: They have the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Spirit as well as their Paſtors. But alas, that men
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:61849:39"/>
ſhould bee ſo ignorant againſt both Scripture and Experience! Indeed God changeth the Will on a ſudden, but he doth not infuſe knowledge, eſpecially of difficult points, on a ſudden. If hee do,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 5.39. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.2.11 <hi>Pſalm</hi> 1.2.</note> why are we command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſearch and ſtudy the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and meditate on them day and night? Did they ever know any that was ſuddenly made ſo wiſe, except it were on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his own conceit? O cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed pride, that will not ſuffer one godly man of many, to know that hee is ſo ignorant; and that knowledge cannot bee had ſo eaſily! But I expect not that the more ſilly ignorant Profeſſors ſhould apprehend this or any other Truth, though it bee delivered never ſo plainely or evidently.<note place="margin">Auguſt. de Trin. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>1</hi>
                  </note> It is <hi>Auguſtines</hi> ruled caſe, <hi>Nullus hominum ita locutus eſt, ut in omnibus ab om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus intelligeretur:</hi> No man ſpake ſo plaine, that in all things hee was underſtood by all men. Pride ever thinks it cannot err, and that rather all the world is
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:61849:40"/>
dark, then it ſelfe blind. The proud Phariſees would not admit that Chriſt ſhould preach any thing worthy of admiration;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 7.47. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3 12</note> therefore they concluded, that their Officers were deceived. Pride makes men ſo blind and ſtupid, that they cannot be ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of any the moſt excellent graces in thoſe they hate. It was the Phariſees proud opinion of themſelves, that cauſed them to deſpiſe others, diſſenting from their Impiety and unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe.<note place="margin">Aug. Conf. lib. <hi>10.</hi> c. <hi>12</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Rideat me iſta dicentem, qui illa non ſentit, &amp; ego doleam ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentem me.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:61849:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> We are bound to the Duty of determined Church-communion by the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of Apoſtolick and Pimitive times.</head>
               <p n="1">§. 1. SEventhly; And yet we have for the ſame Point, the churches cuſtomes clear enough, which hath ever been counted to have ſolid Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Every Society, beſides their Lawes in Books, have their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes alſo in practice; and theſe not to be taken up or laid downe at every mans pleaſure. We may not reject that cuſtom:<note place="margin">Tertul. de Vel. Virgin. c. <hi>2</hi> Pandect. <hi>1.</hi> Tit. <hi>3.</hi> de Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge <hi>35.</hi>
                  </note> which we cannot condemn, ſaith <hi>Tertullian.</hi> The civil Law ſaith, <hi>Imo magnae au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritatis hoc jus habetur; quod in tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum probatum eſt, ut non fuerit ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to comprehendere neceſſe.</hi> Cuſtomes
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:61849:41"/>
are of ſo great authority, that men remember them without book, and writ them not as they do their Lawes or Statutes. Now as eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Society, ſo the Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides her Lawes, hath her cuſtoms too. I add, that the Apoſtles and their chuches had their cuſtomes. For about thirty years after Chriſts Aſcenſion, the Apoſtle pleadeth cuſtome; <hi>We</hi> (that is, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles) <hi>have no ſuch cuſtome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16</note> 
                  <hi>neither the Churches of God.</hi> If ſo few years were enough to make a cuſtome, ſhall it not much more be a cuſtom after above Sixteen hundred and fifty years? A cuſtom is ſuſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible of more and leſſe; the longer it runneth, the more ſtrength it gathereth. <hi>Conſuetudo etiam in civilibus rebus pro Lege ſuſcipitur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tertull. de Cor. Milit. c. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>cum deſicit Lex;</hi> it is <hi>Tertullians</hi> Rule: Cuſtome is received for a Law, even in civil buſineſſes, where there is no Law. Moreover, as the church hath cuſtomes, ſo ſtands up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and fears not to repeat them. <hi>Moſes,</hi> as a Law-giver, one would think, would be all for Law, yet he is <hi>poſitivè</hi> ful for cuſtom too.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.32.</note> 
                  <hi>Ask now of the dayes that are paſt
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:61849:41"/>
which were before thee, ſince the day that God created man upon the earth; and ask from the one ſide of heaven unto the other, whether there hath been any ſuch thing. Job</hi> is for it too; <hi>Enquire of the former age,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 8.8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and prepare thy ſelf to the ſearch of their fathers (for we are but of yeſterday) ſhall not they teach thee?</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets do the ſame; for <hi>Jeremy</hi> ſaith, <hi>Stand ye in the wayes, and ſee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.16.</note> 
                  <hi>and ask for the old paths, where is the good way, and walk therein.</hi> To all theſe agreeable is that of the Fathers, took up in the firſt Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene Councel, and which ever ſince hath been the churches cry, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Let old cuſtomes prevail.</hi> Thus you ſee cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome hath been counted a ſound allegation, from the beginning of the world.</p>
               <p n="2">§ 2 Now, that determined church-communion was the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of the Primitive chriſtians, appeareth,</p>
               <p>Firſt, The ſervants of God were all with one accord in <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> porch, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.12.<note place="margin">Diodat. in loc.</note> There was their appointed place or ordinary meeting, there to preach to the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:61849:42"/>
People. None among them pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to go to any other place to hear any other Teachers:<note place="margin">Engl. Ann. in locum</note> None among them preſumed to forſake their own publick Aſſembly; or in neglect thereof, to frequent other Congregations; much leſſe any private Conventicle. Yea, the place of their meeting ſhewed their conſtant reſolution, to teſtifie the truth of Jeſus, from which no fear or danger could then deterr them. The Rulers of the Synagogue, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.15, ſent to deſire <hi>Paul</hi> and his company to ſpeak a word of exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, before the Apoſtle opened his mouth. For as no man might preſume in thoſe dayes to preach without lawful Authority, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thereto by the Governours by God appointed; it being the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and practice of the Gnoſticks (the moſt hateful of all Hereticks) that the Miniſteral function might be exerciſed by any man:<note place="margin">Iren. l. <hi>4</hi> c. <hi>5</hi>
                  </note> So nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were Congregations then without ſome Government; for in every Synagogue it appeareth there were ſome Rulers,<note place="margin">Eng. Ann. on Jer. <hi>2.39</hi>
                  </note> who reſtrained extravagant gadders, that did ſo god to and fro, that like backſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:61849:42"/>
                  <hi>Iſrael,</hi> they oft took a new way in Gods ſervice. Anarchical licentiouſneſs is a late ſprung up Muſhroom.</p>
               <p n="3">§ 3 Next, hear how <hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Clem. Rom. Ep. ad Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth. p. <hi>2.</hi> &amp; <hi>73.</hi>
                  </note> the ancienteſt (and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a faithful Witneſſe) of all thoſe whom we call Fathers, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth this cuſtom. The main ſcope of his Epiſtle is to exhort the Corinthians, a Factious people, to ſubmit themſelves to their own Paſtors, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. His Argument whereby he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadeth them to this Duty, is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide other,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 57.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: Lawful and laborious (for of ſuch he ſpeaketh) Miniſters can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be rejected, but wrongfully and injuriouſly. Thereafter he asketh this Queſtion, What kind of men are they that forſake or deſpiſe their Overſeers and Miniſters?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 59</note> He anſwereth, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; only the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and full of all wickedneſſe. Then he addeth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 61</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; Your ſeparation from him perverted ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:61849:43"/>
Whereas on the contrary he telleth his Corinthians; That the height (of grace and glory) unto which love (towards their own o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeers) advanceth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 64</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it is unexpreſſible. Now all this, and much more, he alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to confirme his former propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 2 <hi>ct</hi> 73</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Submit your ſelves obediently unto your owne Miniſters.</p>
               <p>Hath then this ill cuſtome of forſaking our Miniſters, in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of their function, laſted long?<note place="margin">Be Hall Vowes cent. <hi>2.</hi> Sect. <hi>98.</hi>
                  </note> I ſay as our Engliſh <hi>Seneca,</hi> it is more then time it were abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated; age is an aggravation to ſin. Hereſie or abuſe, if it be gray-headed, deſerves ſharper oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. To ſay, I will do ill, becauſe I have done ſo, is perilous and impious preſumption. Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance can no more make any wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe ſafe, then the Author of ſin, no Divel.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <note place="margin">Sozom. Hiſt l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi> in fin.</note>§ 4. Laſtly, <hi>Sozomen</hi> writeth, that it was a cuſtome in <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> that though one Paſtor had the overſight of the reſt, yet every
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:61849:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
particular Paſtor did govern their particular churches, and gathered their people unto their ſeveral Congregations.<note place="margin">Euſ. de vit. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>63</hi> Soz. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>30.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, publiſhed a Law, that no Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, and hereticks ſhould aſſemble themſelves or meet together either publickly or privately in any place, but in their Parochial churches, and with their appointed and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Paſtor: and that Hiſtorian ſaith, that by that Law the very memory of moſt of thoſe Sectaries was forgotten and extinguiſhed. This noble Act of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> is in effect mentioned alſo by <hi>Sozomen.</hi> The ſame <hi>Sozomen</hi> reporteth, that <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Great decreed (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving firſt torn the Petitions of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries) that they ſhould not aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble together,<note place="margin">Sozo. lib. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> but in the Orthodoxe congregations; much leſs that they ſhould profeſſe their Het<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rodoxe Doctrine, or Ordaine Paſtors: but ſhould be baniſhed from their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations, diſgraced by ſome Infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and not be partakers of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon priviledges and Favours with others. In that Panegyrical Speech,<note place="margin">Euſeb. Hiſt. l. <hi>10.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi> circ. med.</note> mentioned by <hi>Euſebius,</hi> this cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:61849:44"/>
is not only confirmed, but hyperbolically demonſtrated, to be immediatly ſubordinate to the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the High Prieſt of our profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion Chriſt Jeſus; ſo that I need not any more to commemorate the power that a faithful ordinary Paſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or hath over his charge and people. This I have ſo briefly intimated, not only becauſe they that are in Authority may, and muſt occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally mention their Authority;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.1</note> for ſo did the Apoſtles: but alſo that the Revilers of the Miniſters of Chriſt, with whom this vitious age aboundeth, may know what power Miniſters had, both in the Apoſtles time, and for many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years after (as they may read in holy <hi>Cyprian</hi> and others) even when Miniſterial cenſures were farre more rigid then now they are,<note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Baxters Reſt, part <hi>2</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> and when no Magiſtrate did ſecond them; yea when it was an hazard to their lives to be known chriſtians: And yet now, when chriſtianity is in credit, even thoſe that ſeeme Religious, do judge Chriſts diſcipline to be Tyranny and proud domination.</p>
               <p n="5">§ 5. Cuſtome then may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:61849:44"/>
againſt them that contend againſt Parochial church-commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. No reaſoning with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious; it will be to ſmall pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. None ſo ready a way to ſtop their mouths, as cuſtome. The Apoſtle uſing it againſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious <hi>[If any man ſeem to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious]</hi> teacheth us to uſe it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the like: Specially,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16</note> if the Matter be by nature (as this is) of circumſtance and outward Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; for a wrangling wit will elude all uſe of Reaſon. It is well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved of the Philoſopher,<note place="margin">Ariſt. phyſ. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>2</hi> &amp; aliis ſape</note> that in Moral Matters, men may not look for Mathematical proofs; the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Subject will not beare them. If not in moral, much leſs in Ritual; they of all other, are leaſt ſuſceptible of a demonſtrative Reaſon. The Apoſtle ſaw this, and therefore reſolves all into the churches practiſe, by cuſtome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in this kind: enough of it ſelfe, to ſhew that the Churches cuſtome ſhall ever be of force, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verrule ſuch as are conten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ious. Yet we do not compare cuſtomes, much leſſe, oppoſe them to Scripture. We ſay as <hi>Cyprian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cypr. Ep. <hi>63</hi>
                  </note> We muſt not
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:61849:45"/>
follow the cuſtome of man, but the Verity of God.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.2 <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.3.</note> Yea, <hi>Wo to him that followeth a multitude to do E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.</hi> For the cuſtomes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are vaine. Never any cuſtome againſt Scripture. Nay, <hi>Conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo ſinc Veritate, vetuſtas Erroris eſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cyp. Ep. <hi>74.</hi>
                  </note> ſaith <hi>Cyprian</hi> againe: Cuſtom without Verity, is the oldneſſe of Errour. By this then we may ſee, we have a ground for what we do in Parochial Church-communion. We do no more then the churches of God. So our ears may here the voice in <hi>Eſay,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.21.</note> behind us, <hi>This is the way, walk in it;</hi> As you do, you are in the right, and there hold you.</p>
               <p n="6">§ 6. But we do commonly much miſtake in one evil cuſtome, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the different Gifts and Qualifications of our Miniſters. Now, if unto every one of us Grace be given according to the meaſure of the gift of Chriſt: if all diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of grace proceed from the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Chriſts gift,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.7.</note> none ought to repine at anothers gifts, nor be proud of his own.<note place="margin">Concil. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſp. Can. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> For that were to imagine as <hi>Pelagians</hi> affirmed, that grace is given according to
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:61849:45"/>
Merit of condignity or congruity. But heare what <hi>Nazianzene</hi> ſaith concerning this:<note place="margin">Naz. Orat. <hi>40.</hi> p. <hi>556.</hi>
                  </note> Enquire not what the Authority is, or Dignity of thy Teacher; Any one is ſufficient to inſtruct thee, who is approved, who is not openly condemned, nor rejected from the church. Thou who haſt need to be healed, judge not thy Judges, nor vilifie the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of them, by whom thou art cleanſed; neither make a difference between them that beget thee in Chriſt. One indeed is better then another, and one is inferior to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; but conſider: If two Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Rings, the one of Gold, the other of Iron, each of them having engraven the Emperours Image, do imprint the Wax; what doth the one Seale differ from the other? No thing at all: Diſcerne then the matter in the Wax, how witty ſoever thou art. Thus holy <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzen.</hi> Miniſters indeed have their particular Gifts given them: To one thus, to another thus. One meaſure fitteth not every Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4</note> but of theſe ſome are more Excellent, ſome leſſe. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> were not alike gifted.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 14.12</note> As
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:61849:46"/>
there are Mettals, ſome of Gold, ſome of Silver; ſo gifts in Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.<note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bain on Eph. <hi>3.7.</hi>
                  </note> I conclude this in the words of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Bayne:</hi> Now, to make no difference, but to embark all in one bottome, hath more good affection, then ſound judgement. Though there be diverſities of Gifts in Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, ſome more, ſome leſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, yet we muſt neither immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately admire the one, nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derprize the other. There are peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple affected both wayes; ſome that think it enough to give their names to ſuch a man, and to cry down o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in compariſon of him who hath the moſt parts; theſe perſons have no true taſt of the gifts of him whom they extol; for the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering at their perſon keep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th from taſting the Gifts: As if a cup of wine were ſet down, while we look at the curious workmanſhip of the cup; ſo they. Others think ſo baſely of them, as if they could ſay nothing worth the hearing. Some on the other hand, becauſe God doth all in all, they make no diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the Inſtrument; but are offend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d with them, that look more at one then another. Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:61849:46"/>
theſe, there is the true way; neither ſo to love thoſe who have the greateſt, as to deſpiſe the other; nor to love the leſſer, ſo as not to love there more, where God loveth more; and to bleſſe him more (though we do it in all) where he hath diſtributed more Grace and favour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Reaſon teacheth that Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined Church-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion is a Carnal Glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the worthineſſe or Excellency of other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors, above their own.</head>
               <p n="1">§ 1. EIghthly and laſtly. I will add ſome Reaſons: For Faith is a rational Act of a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional creature. And that is the ſtrongeſt Faith, which hath the ſtrongeſt Reaſons to prove the Teſtimony to be valid upon which it reſteth, and the cleareſt appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:61849:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and uſe of thoſe Reaſons. Yea,<note place="margin">M. Baxters Reſt, part <hi>2</hi> p. <hi>207.</hi>
                  </note> that is the trueſt Faith which hath the trueſt Reaſons truly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend and uſed. Reaſon recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied is the Eye of the Soul, and the Guide of our Life. The uſe of the Word, and all Ordinances and Providences, is firſt to rectifie Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and thereby the Will, and thereby the Life. I ſay againe, Faith it ſelf is an Act of Reaſon: or elſe it is a brutiſh Act, and not humane. He that hath the right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Reaſon, hath the moſt Grace, Sincerity (and conſequently our Salvation) lyeth in the ſtrength and prevalency of rectified Reaſon over the Fleſh, and its intereſt and deſires. I do then reſolve my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renetical confutation into this Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional concluſion: It is a groſs and carnal thing to glory in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs and excellency of them that diſpence the Myſteries of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Now, that ſeparation from Parochial Church-communion is guilty of groſſe errour, apppeareth by theſe Reaſons.</p>
               <p n="2">§ 2. Firſt, It ſeeks to eclipſe and obſcure the glory of God. God hath appointed all Meanes
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:61849:47"/>
and creatures to illuſtrate and brighten his Glory. He that dares ſet it upon the creatures head muſt needs be guilty of <hi>leſe</hi> Majeſty, in an high degree. This is all the honour left to us, <hi>Obſequii Gloria,</hi> the honour to obey,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.8. <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.23.</note> to be wholly ſubject to ſo great and good a God, and to give all glory to him. Now he that made us, and knowes our mold, and faſhioned the weakneſſe and frailty of our Nature, choſe to himſelf ſo weak an Inſtrument, that by the few words of a fraile and ignorant man a precious and immortal Soul ſhould be eternally ſaved; which moſt Divines make a greater work, then that of creation: that ſo we might be neceſſitated to look high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to the powerful hand of God, that brings ſo great things to paſs. Thus hath he choſen,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.27, 28.</note> not only <hi>fooliſh things,</hi> and <hi>weak</hi> things, but <hi>things that are not,</hi> to bring to naught things that are. A ſtrange Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox: and enough to amaze an <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> to heare of a <hi>Non Ens</hi> annihilating an <hi>Ens.</hi> Yet, the things which are not at all in mens apprehenſion, do give the light of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:61849:48"/>
the glory of God in the face of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6, 7</note> The Lord could have made his Seraphim, or other An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1.24.</note> even in this ſenſe Miniſtring Spirits, for the good of them that ſhould be Heires of Salvation: but then we ſhould have been took up too much with the glittering brightneſſe of the creature. Why then do we gaze on <hi>Paul,</hi> he doth but plant? or glory in <hi>Apollos,</hi> he doth but water? Why do we run to others of inferior parts in other Congregations? What is this but to oppoſe the Almighty, and to counterplot Wiſdome it ſelfe? Now judge you, whether this be not a groſs and carnal Error, or not.</p>
               <p n="3">§ 3. Secondly, It detracts from the Word of God: from its Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and from its Efficacy. 1. From its Majeſty; in that the Word of God is made to ſtoop to mans fancy. It is a ſigne, men never received the love of the Truth, when plaine Truth cannot pleaſe them; but it muſt be ſet out in ſuch attyre, as may beſt ſatisfie their Eye. And unleſſe the Word of God, as the Jewes tell us of the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:61849:48"/>
Manna, though fabulouſly (that whatſoever character or Idea of taſt a man ſhapt to himſelfe in his fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,<note place="margin">Wiſd. <hi>6.20, 21.</hi> Ainſw. on Exod.</note> when he was eating the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, it ſerved to the Appetite of the Eater, and was tempered to every ones liking) have ſo many ſeveral reliſhes agreeable to every ones li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, even this, though Angels food, ſhall be loathed. And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this argues a carnal heart. Though <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Apollos</hi> were of admirable endowments, yet the Word of God is embraced by ſome, when coming from one; and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, when publiſhed by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. It was the ſame Truth,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12</note> but not in the ſame dreſs. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> tels us of two in his time, a Greek,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> and a Chriſtian, that were very hot in diſpute, whether <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>Plato,</hi> were the better Scholler. The Chriſtian he amplifies S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Pauls</hi> Wiſdome and Excellency; the Greek ſcornes him as rude and ſimple, and his writings not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to <hi>Plato</hi>'s Philoſophical and lofty ſtile. The Father hee comes in as it were to moderate; and when he had magnified St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s learning, he ſeems to chide
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:61849:49"/>
the Chriſtian, that he did not yeild the other what he would have. Grant indeed that <hi>Paul</hi> came in a more plaine and unlearned way, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. That aſpertion was the praiſe, not the diſgrace, but the honour of the Apoſtles. What! Muſt the Royal Law bow to man? Muſt the Word, which muſt ſearch the conſcience, tickle the Fancy? Are not theſe men of itching Eares. And judge you, whether theſe be not carnal. 2. From its Efficacy. The Goſpel ſhines with it own beames, and needs not borrow light from any man; for it is gloriouſly cloathed with ſuch ornaments as Chriſt hath put upon it: when God had once writ with his own finger upon the Tables of Stone, they need no humane po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing. But then, the quickening power of the Spirit muſt goe along with it. Unleſſe the <hi>arm of the Lord be revealed,</hi> there is none will <hi>beleeve our report.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſa.</hi> 53.1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4.</note> The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle tels us <hi>of a demonſtration</hi> of the Spirit. Now a <hi>demonſtration</hi> (as the Philoſopher hath it) is
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:61849:49"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a native gloſs of Truth; which clearely ſhewes it,<note place="margin">Ariſtot. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalytic. Poſter. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> and preſently convinceth a man, there is no diſputing againſt a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration.</hi> Why then do men attribute ſo much unto man, as if the Word were a dead letter, till quickned by his endowments? As if <hi>Paul</hi> did not only plant, but bleſs; And <hi>Apollos</hi> not only wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but gave the increaſe; and God in the mean while did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but ſtood as a Spectator. When as indeed, <hi>Paul</hi> is but at the beſt, the Lords Eccho, that never ſpeaks till it be ſpoken unto. And are not theſe carnal, that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying in the Endowments of Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, take from the Word of God the Efficacy of it, as well as the Majeſtie of it.</p>
               <p n="4">§ 4. Thirdly, It breeds Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and Diviſions in the Church. Now,</p>
               <p>Firſt, Schiſmes doe hinder the Communion of Saints. For all communion flowes from Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And Diviſion deſtroyes Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Some make Unity, the very Forme of being, but ſure it tends to the well being of the Church.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:61849:50"/>
But when one ſhall ſay, I am of <hi>Calvin,</hi> and another I am of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> when as they might both meet in the Name of Chriſtian: Nay, when by moſt ridiculous Diſſention (for we have heard of ſuch a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) when one ſhall ſay,<note place="margin">Culverwel of Schiſm.</note> I am of <hi>Martin;</hi> and another, I am of <hi>Luther;</hi> whereas they did but divide <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> for they were both of his Religion; What muſt this needs bring, but a deformity and confuſion upon the face of the Church, enough to make up a Chaos?</p>
               <p>Secondly, Theſe ſchiſms and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions ſtop the progreſſe of the Goſpel. If Chriſtians would do but as the Cretians cuſtome was, (whence <hi>Syncretiſmus</hi>) to joyn their diviſions againſt ſome common e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, then there would be an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py <hi>Synchriſtianiſmus:</hi> When the hearts, and tongues, and pens of all them that profeſſe the ſame faith in ſincerity, would agree a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, and wholly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the main adverſary; How quickly would the Goſpel then flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and every mountain amongſt us become a plain, the ſeven hils a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:61849:50"/>
the reſt? How ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one,<note place="margin">Eunap. in John <hi>8.56</hi>
                  </note> in conſideration of ſo happy a time, have <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Eunapius</hi> ſpeaks, a ſweet chorus or company of well tuned affections? and a Spirit tripudiating for joy, as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> did <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, when he foreſaw Chriſts day. But until we forget to ſay, <hi>I am of Paul,</hi> and <hi>I am of Apollos,</hi> we are not like to hear the joyfull acclamation of <hi>Grace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Grace,</hi> in the progreſſe of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Schiſms and diviſions give great advantage to our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to ſet up the Kingdom of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan.<note place="margin">Soz. l. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> It was the ſaying of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> the Great, <hi>Diſſention in the Church a is greater evill then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> The Church thus becomes militant againſt herſelf, and the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy becomes triumphant. The Church then for peace hath great bitterneſſe;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.17</note> Whereupon <hi>Bernard</hi> playeth no leſſe elegantly then mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally:<note place="margin">Bern. in Cantic. Ser. <hi>35.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Amaritudo mea amara prius in nece Martyrum; amarior poſt in conflictu Haereticorum; amariſſima nunc in moribus domeſticorum:</hi> The bitterneſſe of the Church firſt was
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:61849:51"/>
bitter in the death of Martyrs; next more bitter in her conflict againſt Hereticks; but moſt bitter then, when her children have a <hi>form of godlineſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.8.</note> 
                  <hi>but deny the power of it in their lives.</hi> Oh that we could learn of Satan, and his agents ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate to him; to have a ſtrict union and confederacy among our ſelves; as that in <hi>Job</hi> is uſually allegorized,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job.</hi> 41.15.</note> 
                  <hi>The ſcales of Leviathan are ſhut together as with a cloſe ſeal;</hi> in reſpect of their ſecrecie and combinations.</p>
               <p>But further, as it gives this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral advantage, ſo more ſpecially, it is the original of all Errours, and in-let of all Hereſies: When men by a ſtrange <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or reſpect of perſons, ſhall ſet up ſome one as an Oracle; if ſuch a one broach an Error, oh how gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily do they drink it, as if it were ſome ſaving Truth! The Divel thus ſerves many, as <hi>Agrippina</hi> did <hi>Claudius;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tacit. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. l. <hi>12.</hi> in ſinc.</note> he mingles poiſon in their delicate meat, and they fall to it with an appetite. So long then as men glory in other Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, beſides their ordinary Paſtors, are they not carnal? for this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:61849:51"/>
breeds Schiſms, which ſtops the progreſſe of the Goſpel, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the communion of Saints, and giveth great advantage to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and originall to all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Some ſinful Effects and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequents of Parochiall Church-Separation.</head>
               <p n="1">§. 1. AS it is moſt agreeable to the dictates of Reaſon, that a people in a vicinity or neighbourhood dwelling together, ought to joyne with thoſe of that neighbourhood, according to their beſt convenience, for participati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of divine Ordinances: So Chriſtians by Providence ſeated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe that are in covenant by a viſible <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> and joyning in Ordinances, muſt much rather make it their buſineſs to reform a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes that are found in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:61849:52"/>
then by any means withdraw from their <hi>Parochiall Churches.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">M. Baxters Anſ. to Mr. Eyre. p. <hi>35.</hi>
                  </note> For whoſoever doth deny that the Pariſhes in <hi>England</hi> are true Churches, he doth more then judg a particular brother, and more then he is able to make good, and more then the Brethren of <hi>New-England</hi> would affirm. And this is the <hi>Third</hi> and laſt part of my Task, to ſhew that the practice I oppoſe,<note place="margin">Tertull. de Praeſc. c. <hi>43</hi>
                  </note> is <hi>contrary to Diſcipline;</hi> which is <hi>Doctrinae Index,</hi> the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt diſcoverer of <hi>Doctrine:</hi> ſo that the quality of Faith is valued according to the converſation. And firſt,</p>
               <p n="2">§ 2. That we might ſhun the fearful Effects and conſequences of Church-Separation, we find frequent advice in Scripture,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.13.</note> To <hi>conſider one another, provoking to love, and to good works:</hi> To <hi>exhort one another daily:</hi> To <hi>comfort our ſelves together,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ</hi> 5.11</note> 
                  <hi>and edifie one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.20.</note> To <hi>warn them that are unru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to comfort feeble minded,</hi> to <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the weak:</hi> To <hi>convert Sinners from the error of their wayes.</hi> All theſe precepts do argue an holy zeal for God, and hatred of Sin
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:61849:52"/>
in our ſelves, and bowels of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion toward others. We read of Separation from Sin and fleſhly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filements, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.27. But we read not of any Separation from Church-communion, and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip in Ordinances given thus in charge, nor of any preſidents go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before us in it:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jude</hi> 19.</note> But we read of an heavie brand laid upon Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiſts. As it is againſt all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of Reaſon, that a people ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered at a great diſtance ſhould combine themſelves in a church way for Sacred Ordinances; ſo it is clear againſt the Scriptures. I grant that Cohabitation or dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling together maketh not up a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational church; for Infidels and Pagans may cohabit, and may make an Idol-church, but not a Church of God: Yet cohabitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is one Ingredient. Saints co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitating, that is (in the New Teſtament language) people ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated for God, not Jewes nor Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſtians, and joyning in Ordinances (as in duty they ought) are a Congregational church.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 2 et 3</note> We find ſeven ſeveral E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> written
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:61849:53"/>
from Heaven to ſeven ſeveral chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; all which had their abode at the place, where the church bore its Name: theſe are Scripture chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Now, if any one church be made up of chriſtians, ſome inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting at one of theſe places, ſome at another, ſome at a third place, ſcarce three of one Town, no more then of one mind; here is not Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture Order, which is of God, but Apocryphal confuſion.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.</note> As then a Paſtor ought to watch over his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and his people ought to obey and attend to their Paſtor; ſo this is impoſſible to be done by confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed running to hear as every one liketh, in a diſtracted church-Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, contrary to the Ordin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God and good Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates. Exceptions indeed may be taken at the overlarge extent and diſordered ſituation of divers Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial congregations: But Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Aſſemblies (not the name but the thing) is the way that comes up to the Rule of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Light of Reaſon, and the Preſidents of Primitive times. Our congregational Bretheren will have the limit of a Particular
<note place="margin">Mr. Blakc. Cov. Cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:61849:53"/>
church, to be within that number of perſons, that may congregate in one place for Ordinances: If this be yeilded, then it will eaſily be proved, that Pariſh-congregations are of Divine Inſtitution; and then it will conſequently be true, that peoples Separation from Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial Church-communion hath this Sinful Effect, to be a Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly confuſion, contrary to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitution. For, <hi>Contiguas pictas juſſit habere domos:</hi> Saints that made up a church, were ſtill Saints in cohabitation; they were as in faith, ſo in Habitation joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together.</p>
               <p n="3">§ 3. It were eaſie to relate the abundant fearful Effects and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful conſequents, which this Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Church-Separation doth produce; as the diſorderly confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which of neceſſity it doth oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion: the weakning of the work of the Lord in the place where providence hath ſeated them,<note place="margin">Mr. Blake, loco ſupra citato.</note> and conferred many Mercies upon them: the depriving of Paſtors of their Flock, Spiritual Parents of their Children: the animoſity of Spirit, that is wrought in thoſe
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:61849:54"/>
that withdraw themſelves, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them whom they leave as ſcarce Miniſters of Chriſt, nor their congregations as churches of Chriſt; withdrawing then and thence, when and where Chriſt is pleaſed to reſide. I do only urge this, that it is without all Scripture precept or preſident, to depart from the ſolemn and publick worſhip of God, to which his ſpecial provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath bound us. It was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted dangerous, not only to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimate one Apoſtle above another, as Papiſts do Saint <hi>Peter;</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the ancient practice and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the church in <hi>Tertullians</hi> time;<note place="margin">Ter. de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrip. c. <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Non mihi tam bene eſt, imo non mihi tam male eſt, ut Apoſtolos inter ſe committam;</hi> I am not ſo wiſe (ſaith he;) nay, I am not ſo fooliſh, as to value one Apoſtle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove another: But it was thought dangerous alſo to eſteem one Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or Teacher (in the Greek or Latin church) as if he had the mind of Chriſt above another,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16</note> as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh. The Greek Menologie mentions a Diviſion (like that among the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans) in the Greek church, in the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:61849:54"/>
daies of the Emperour <hi>Alexius:</hi> In which one preferred <hi>Baſil,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>An.</hi> 1103.</note> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gloried in <hi>Nazianzone,</hi> a third extolled <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> until they heard this voice from heaven, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, We are all one before God. It is dangerous then, to extol one of the ſervants of Chriſt, who ſpeaks according to the Spirit of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Doroth. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lioth. Patr. Tom. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> above ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: leſt (as the Hiſtorian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth) ſuch Admirers become <hi>Miriones;</hi> that is, like to the man, who firſt magnified <hi>Zoſimus,</hi> next <hi>Macarius,</hi> then the Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> laſtly the Bleſſed Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which alſo (blinded through Inconſtancy) he renounced total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and finally. This is our fear, this is our complaint.</p>
               <p n="4">§ 4. This Error of Indetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned church-communion was of old taken for a conſequent, yea, a ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptome of Luxury and Wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. It was obſerved of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians, that they were rich and luxurious; and therefore proud and contentious; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and ſo on, as <hi>Strabo</hi> deſcribeth them.<note place="margin">Strab. Geor. l. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> We ſhould therefore beware of ſuch Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:61849:55"/>
as a Mark of Spiritual Wantonneſſe. And we find in <hi>Heſychius,</hi> that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is no better then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Thus you may ſee the Genius or Inclination of what people is ſtrongly bent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Sin. And though it be true that Grace doth not only po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Nature (Morality knoweth how to do that) but even ſubdue it, and change the very frame and conſtitution of it; yet being that it is not wholly conquered in this life, it is like, it will ſhew it ſelfe moſt in ſome domineering corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,<note place="margin">Ball againſt Can.</note> which generally reign a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſtians. This Error tendeth to the renting of the church, the diſgrace of Religion, the advancement of pride, Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, contention, Offence of the Weak, Grief of the Godly, Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Wicked, and riſing againe of Antichriſtianiſme. For they that voluntarily depart from their determined congregations, if in words they do not maintaine Antichriſt, really they do him more credit, then his chief upholders. Seeing of neceſſity they muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that in other churches,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:61849:55"/>
(which may be Antichriſtian, for any thing they know) the pure Faith may be entirely profeſſed, the Doctrine of Salvation plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully preached, the Seals of the Covenant rightly adminiſtred, for ſubſtance; and by the bleſſing of God upon his own Meanes, Chriſtian Soules ordinarily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted and nouriſhed unto eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life: Which is more then all the Factors for Antichriſt ſhall ever be able to make good. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this account it ſeemeth the Council held at <hi>Nantes,</hi> decreed,<note place="margin">Conc. Nan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. c. <hi>1.</hi> et. <hi>2</hi> Anno. <hi>800.</hi> Grat. cauſa <hi>9.</hi> qu. <hi>2.</hi> Can In Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicis.</note> that no Paſtor ſhould admit unto Divine Ordinances, any man of another congregation, that wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly deſpiſed the Dvine Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of his Ordinary Miniſter. And <hi>Gratian</hi> reporteth, that to the ſame effect and purpoſe one <hi>Canon</hi> was eſtabliſhed in <hi>Concilio Meldenſi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">§ 5. Unto all theſe I could add <hi>Muſculus</hi> his judgment, who relateth five dangerous conſequents of this Error.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That it caſteth the Soul in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to danger of its Salvation, while as it departeth from communion
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:61849:56"/>
with the appointed and approved Congregation.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">Muſeu. Loc. Comm. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap>hiſmate.</note>2. That it divideth (as much as in it lyeth) the whole and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire body of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That it deſpiſeth not one or two chriſtians, but the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, which it forſaketh.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That it doth not only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe, but condemn that congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, as not genuine, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterate.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That it violates the bond of Peace, which is charity, in that it not only departeth, but ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth others to depart from their proper and peculiar congregation. All which are confirmed and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified by that Pious Divine. How dangerous this Error is, may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be declared by many teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Judicious <hi>Calvin:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Calv. Inſtit. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> per totum. prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertim. § <hi>§ 4. 10.</hi>
                  </note> Who often telleth us, that ſo highly doth the Lord regard the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of his church, that he count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them Traitors and Fugitives, who contumaciouſly ſeparate from any Society or congregation, which maintaineth the true Miniſtery of the Word and Sacraments. And that ſo highly the Lord eſteemeth
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:61849:56"/>
his church, That whoſoever wrongeth her authority, he jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth it derogatory to his own Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, &amp;c. But I ſtudy brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> The cauſes which men pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for Separation from Parochial Church-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, are frivolous and invalid. And Firſt, Indeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined Church-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion is no part, but an Abuſe of Chriſtian Liberty.</head>
               <p n="1">§ 1. CHriſtian Liberty, as it is agreed upon by the learned, is either of the Will, or of the Perſon. Liberty of the Perſon is that which we call chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; and it may be thus deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed:
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:61849:57"/>
Chriſtian Liberty is a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual manumiſſion, whereby the Faithful are by Chriſt delivered from the Tyranny of Sin, the curſe of the Law,<note place="margin">Til<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>n Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tag. part. <hi>2.</hi> diſput. <hi>44.</hi> Th <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> and Wrath of God; from the yoke of <hi>Moſes;</hi> and from the bondage of things Indifferent; that they might free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, willingly, and cheerfully ſerve God, to his Glory, the Edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Bretheren, and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of their own Soules. Here are three parts of this Liberty. 1. From Sin and Eternal Death: 2. From the Levitical ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies: 3. From the obligation of the conſcience in things Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. This laſt alone belongeth to this Diſcourſe: which is called chriſtian, to diſtinguiſh it from civil Liberty, and from the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſſe which many bad chriſtians uſe, being a Liberty of the Fleſh, and not of the Spirit. Concerning this Liberty, wee may obſerve two General Rules.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Synop. Par. Theol. diſp. <hi>35.</hi> Th. <hi>33.</hi> &amp;c.</note>1. That all Indifferent things (in themſelves) are free and lawful for chriſtians to uſe or not to uſe, at their pleaſure.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That a Believer muſt not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:61849:57"/>
uſe and practiſe his chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Liberty;<note place="margin">M. Parr. on Rom. <hi>14.21</hi>
                  </note> but that he ought ſometimes to refraine from it, and to moderate it.</p>
               <p>Now, there are two Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of this Liberty; the one is General, the other is Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</p>
               <p>The Generall Moderators are Faith and charity; which direct when, where, and how it is to be uſed.</p>
               <p>The Special is, Lawful Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, by Sanctions, civil and Eccleſiaſtical: for the civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate may abridge our Liberties in things Indifferent, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good: and the church hath power to determine the uſe of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different Rites and ceremonies in Gods publick Worſhip for the maintaining of good Order and Uniformity.</p>
               <p n="2">§. 2. And now, I hope a weak chriſtian may perceive, that this practice of Indetermined church-communion is a Scandalizing by abuſe of chriſtian Liberty: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a Woe belongs to them that Scandalize others by Abuſe of their Liberty in things Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:61849:58"/>
againſt charity. Our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our (<hi>Luk.</hi> 17.<note place="margin">Eng. Annot in locum.</note>1, 2.) diſcovereth as the Sin of thoſe times (which was, to think it little or no ſin, by their pride, and Imperious importunity to ſcandal or grieve an infirme, poor, or inferiour Brother) ſo alſo the puniſhment of Scandals Given, whether by Word or Deed. For otherwiſe Offences are often taken, by perverſe and ignorant ſoules, from good and laudable things done or ſpoken, becauſe they croſs their blind and corrupt Opinions:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Math.</hi> 11.6.</note> ſo were the Scribes and Phariſees ſcandaled and offended at Chriſts Doctrine and Works of Mercy. Their Puniſhment is, <hi>It were better for him, that a Milſtone were hanged about his neck, and he caſt into the Sea, then that he ſhould offend one of theſe little ones:</hi> that is, it were better for a man thus Scandaling one of the meaneſt of Gods children, to be caſt into the moſt deſperate or helpleſſe condition in this life, then to endure the Eternal tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which await him in Hell. There be then ſome Actions In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:61849:58"/>
ſuch as in their own nature be no ſinne,<note place="margin">Pareus in Rom. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> but may be done or omitted without fault; that is, As there be ſomethings ſimply or abſolutely good, which be comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or forbidden in the Word; ſo ſome be neither good nor evill, in reſpect of the things done, but be of middle quality.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.30. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Rom</hi> 11.36. <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o</hi> 3.16, 17</note> Yet in all indifferent things, the honour of God ought to be our marke to aim at, no leſſe then in actions ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and commanded; and that for theſe reaſons.</p>
               <p n="3">§ 3. Firſt, Becauſe it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Commandment of God, that any man ſhould be a juſt occaſion of ſinning to any other man, either by Word or Deed, to hurt the ſalvation of any,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8, 9, 10. &amp; 10 32</note> or by building them up unto ſin, by evil example in Sayings, or Doings.</p>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.8.</note> It puls down heavy judgments on the ſcandalizing perſons, temporal and eternall, without ſpeedy Repentance.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, It is againſt the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Apoſtle, <hi>If meate make my brother to offend,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.13</note> (ſaith he) <hi>I will eat no fleſh while the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:61849:59"/>
world ſtandeth, leſt I make my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to offend.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, We break the rule of Charity,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.15</note> which is ever carefull not to trouble, or to do the leaſt harm to the ſoul of any Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Wee wound our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours weak conſcience (which is great cruelty) procuring him by our example to allow,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12</note> or do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing whereof in his conſcience he was never reſolved, or which he knew he ought not to doe, had not wee made him to ſtumble: Nay by our Offence we deſtroy our brother,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.15</note> ſo much as lieth in us, and murther his ſoule (either wholly driving him from the faith, or diſcouraging him) for ſo ſlender a thing, as is a thing indifferent.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, It reacheth not to our brother alone,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Co. r.</hi> 8.12 <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.45 <hi>Act.</hi> 9.4.</note> and to his deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but even to Chriſt himſelf, againſt whom we ſinne, in woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any member of his; for ſo ſtrait is the conjunction betweene Chriſt and the Faithfull, that the good or evil offered to them, redounds to him. We ſee then
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:61849:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>
by all theſe Arguments, that ſuch things as in their own Nature be not evil,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.20</note> and which otherwiſe we might do; yet if they prove offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to our brethren, we ought to ſhun them as things ſinful and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful.</p>
               <p n="4">§. 4. Theſe things conſidered, I thus argue: A duty abſolutely neceſſary is not an indifferent duty: but Parochial Church-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion is a duty abſolutely neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: Therfore &amp;c. I mean, <hi>Neceſſitate praecepti.</hi> The Major Propoſition though obvious to many Abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, I confirme thus.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To imagine that a neceſſary duty, is (or can be) an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent duty, is the hight of impiety: this was to fetch power and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage from any ordinance of God, to commit ſinne.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.17 <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.25. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.11 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 36.10.</note> This was the iniquity of <hi>Elies</hi> ſons, of falſe prophet, of <hi>Rabſhekah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. This is the only thing that makes us like the Prophets <hi>Cake, not turned, Hoſh.</hi> 7.8. neither raw not roaſted; Fiſh nor fleſh, in regard of our mixtures and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences in Religion: as it was in <hi>Ahabs</hi> time, when they halted
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:61849:60"/>
between God and <hi>Baal,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.21. as in <hi>Samaria,</hi> when they feared the Lord, and yet ſerved the gods of the Nations, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 17.33. as in <hi>Judah,</hi> when they ſware by the <hi>Lord,</hi> and by <hi>Malcham, Zeph.</hi> 1.5. as in <hi>Laodicea,</hi> neither hot not cold, <hi>Rev</hi> 3.15.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This was the reaſon of the Lords ſevere proceeding in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the Jewes, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.13. their indifferency cauſed their meer formality, in Gods neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary ſervice and worſhip, which they frequented and performed only in regard of humane, either Tradition teaching,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 15.8. <hi>Mark</hi> 7.6.</note> or Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity maintaining or enjoyning it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This was the Jewes end of their Faſting and Humiliation, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.4. to expiate their former ſinful and injurious courſes, that they might return to them more freely again. As <hi>Papiſts</hi> in ſome places are reported to have a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſaying in their mouths; Wee muſt ſin, that we may be ſhriven, and we muſt be ſhriven that we may ſin. The <hi>Minor</hi> I have proved above by Scripture
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:61849:60"/>
Arguments; namely, that Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial Church-Communion is a duty abſolutely neceſſary, implan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by nature, becauſe all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are to joyn themſelves to ſome particular Church viſible, when the Lord offereth occaſion: That we are bound to hearing in our determined Congregations, <hi>Neceſſitate praecepti:</hi> becauſe God aſſigneth unto every ordinary Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor a portion of his people, to be inſtructed by him: becauſe ſeparation from determined Church-communion is reproved, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. Becauſe the Lord commandeth to worſhip him or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, which is not obſerved in indertermined Church-communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Becauſe we are bound to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in our particular Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by Chriſts doctrine and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; by the cuſtome of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick and primitive times; and by rectified reaſon, &amp;c. Unto theſe I could have added Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but I omitted that, becauſe that way is ſubject to corruption and exception; and at long run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the ſtream of the channel carrieth with it many dregges
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:61849:61"/>
of erroneous Innovations, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="5">§. 5. And now I hope, it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that this error is to far from being any part of our Chriſtian Libertie, (as the practiſes of it do pretend, confirming <hi>Honorius Reggias</hi> his authentick and above mentioned Propoſition) that it is oppoſite unto it, at leaſt a ſhameful abuſe of it, and a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious liberty for an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the fleſh,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Jude</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>turning the grace of God into laſciviouſneſſe.</hi> Only with <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> writing on the ſame occaſion, I conclude, that it cannot be any part of Chriſtian liberty;<note place="margin">August. Tom. <hi>4.</hi> Queſt. Ves. &amp; Novi Teſt. q. <hi>61.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Illud autem quod omnino non licet, nec aliquâ neceſſitate mitigatur, ut admiſſum non obſit, eſt ſemper illicitum:</hi> For that which may not any way be done, nor can by any neceſſity be ſo qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified, that it may not be hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full after it be done, is alwaies unlawfull to be done. Therefore, to worſhip God on the Lords day Afternoone and Forenoone, is according to Scripture a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary duty, in our Parochiall Churches; and no indifferent
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:61849:61"/>
matter: And therefore no man ſhould be ſuffered openly to make this knowne plaine Sin his pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice and profeſſion. The Kings that ſuffered the people to worſhip at the high places,<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.43.</note> are reproved; though the Text ſaith,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33 17.</note> that yet they worſhipped only the God of their fathers: and though it was alſo a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted point; our fathers ſay in this mountaine, and you ſay in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> men ought to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, ſaid the woman of <hi>Samaria, John</hi> 4.20.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:61849:62"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> Secondly, Separation from Church-Communion, for the Paſtors knowne Inſufficiency or Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous life, may bee lawfull: otherwiſe it is lamentable, if not intolerable and impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</head>
               <p n="1">§. 1. IT is true, Men pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend many cauſes of their ſeparation from Church-communion, that they may not ſeem to unreaſonable as the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sozom. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note> whoſe violent and viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent endeavour was, that their odious errour might bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived without any ſearch or tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:61849:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>But above all other cauſes, they do aggravate the ignorance and ſcandalous Life of their Miniſter. Though ſuch Accuſers ſhould know, that by all Lawes, civil and Eccleſiaſtical, they that are ignorant, ſcandalous, or of known Inſufficiently in the main work, are to be rejected. This ſhould give them full ſatisfaction. For what men of any conſcience or face of common Honeſty, will withdraw from a Society, meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe of the preſence of ſuch, whom he never accuſed to that ſociety, or proved ſit to be rejected? It may be theſe men do feare in their hearts, juſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Detractors, mentioned in the ancient Canon of the church:<note place="margin">Concil. Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert. Cap. <hi>75.</hi> An. <hi>305.</hi>
                  </note> If any man do accuſe any Biſhop, Paſtor or Deacon, of any falſe Crime which he can not prove, he ſhould not be admitted into chriſtian communion before his death. Furthermore; let him know, that objecteth his Paſtors Infirmities, that he is bound to ſearch his own heart and wayes, and remember what may be ſaid againſt himſelfe, and <hi>caſt the beam
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:61849:63"/>
out of his own eyes;</hi> at leaſt, to cenſure others, as an humble chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, that is ſenſible of his own miſcarriges, and imperfections: and how much allowance the beſt men muſt have, that they may paſs for currant. They who will be Accuſers of others, ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at home: For as ſaith <hi>Nazianzen;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nazia. Ep. <hi>26.</hi> Ceſar.</note> How ſhall they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the ſin of others who have not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, confidence in their own Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. But, as the moſt ravenous and hurtful birds, are commonly moſt quick-ſighted, ſo are the moſt wicked men, moſt ready and skilful to find faults in others. The Eye ſeeth not it ſelfe, nor any thing which is too near it; ſo neither ſee we our own faults, except ſet at ſome diſtance, and in another perſon: ſo <hi>David</hi> ſaw his fault, in the perſon of the rich Oppreſſor,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> till then he could not in himſelfe. We ought not to deſpiſe one another for Natural or common infirmities, when we are daily groaning under them our ſelves, and in the hands of the ſame Phyſician. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:61849:63"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: It is the property of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to be faultleſſe and perfect. If Chriſt would not take us with all our faults, and diſtinguiſh between his own and ours, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us and our ſins, we were loſt. It much concerneth us therefore to have a good opinion of our Teachers. For in this our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our examineth his Diſciples, not concerning his Doctrine, but concerning his Perſon; <hi>Whom do men ſay, that I the Son of man am? Mat.</hi> 16.13. And yet, as Chriſt loves our ſins never the more, for all his incomprehenſible love to us, no more will he allow us to love the ſins of Inſufficient and ſcandalous Miniſters. And as we muſt nor think well of them, ſo neither muſt I ſpeak well of them. Therefore.</p>
               <p n="2">§ 2. If Miniſters be inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent or ſcandalous, all conſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble people ſhould endeavour ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily to caſt them out. Neither ſhould any man plead compaſſion to them: For it is cruel compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which for feare of bringing a man and his Family to poverty,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:61849:64"/>
will both connive at his proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſuch hainous guilt, and at the ſtarving and everlaſting Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of mens ſouls. The devil loves ſuch Mercy as this. In the Primitive times, if any Paſtor (of what degree or quality ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever) did fall away from the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Orthodoxe Church,<note place="margin">Secrat. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> Sozom. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi> Euſeb l. <hi>10.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi> Theod. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> Editionis Latinae Grynaei. Ann. <hi>1570.</hi>
                  </note> into any ſchiſme, or hereſie, or lewdneſſe of Life, he was degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and deprived of all Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Liberties, priviledges and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments. This is not only wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed by <hi>Socrates</hi> in the Synodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Epiſtle of the firſt councel at <hi>Nice;</hi> but alſo recorded by <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius, Sozomen,</hi> and <hi>Theodoret.</hi> Neither may they be forborne or tolerated in their Office upon their Repentance. For as Repentance will never cure their Inſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: So it muſt be a very notable Repentance, that muſt at all (much leſſe ſuddainly) readmit a ſcandalous perſon into the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery. In the Primitive Church, after ſuch hainous ſinning, they would admit him to the Miniſtery no more, were he never ſo peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, though they did admit him,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:61849:64"/>
                  <hi>ad Laicam Communionem,</hi> with the people.<note place="margin">Conc. Car. Anno <hi>258.</hi> et conc. Ro. <hi>3.487.</hi>
                  </note> As for their mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, it is forfeited by all law, Divine and humane, ſeeing it was given them only, as unto Paſtors, for the worke of Chriſt, and ſervice of the Church only, <hi>Quamdiu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e bene geſſerint;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo farre as they are able (ſaith a Pious, Judicious,<note place="margin">Mr. Baxter concord. p. <hi>107.</hi>
                  </note> and learned late Writer) they ſhould make the Church reſtitution of the profits and emolumets, which for ſo many yeares they have ſo unjuſtly received: it being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God but plain robbery, and one of the moſt hateful kinds of robbery that can be imagined, to ſtarve and deſtroy mens ſouls, and thus to takes hire for it.</p>
               <p>Moreover, ſeeing the ſincere keeping Covenant with God in Chriſt, is a chief part of our Chriſtian Religion, and a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of abſolute neceſſity to our ſalvation; It is as hard truſting the guidance of that man againe, who hath once betrayed us and the Church unto ſinne and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; as it is to truſt a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander who once turned traitor,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:61849:65"/>
and would deliver up his Army to the power of the Enemie. Nature teacheth to forſake ſuch Commanders, in obedience to their Supreme Soveraigne, and for ſafety of our ſelves.<note place="margin">Eng. Ann. en Eccl. <hi>19.22.</hi>
                  </note> Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, An ignorant or ſcandalous Paſtor, is ſo farre from being a gracious Mediator between God and his people (as he ſhould be) that he is like to draw rather wrath upon himſelf, then procure fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour for them. Yea, the Poet telleth us, that they endanger their flocks;<note place="margin">Homer. Odyſ. l. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Evil ſhepherds infect their flocks. They who ſinne in Gods Houſe or Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.3.</note> are ſaid to <hi>provoke the Lord to his face, and to do evil before his eyes;</hi> as if a Servant ſhould doe things directly croſſe to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters mind and command, to his face. Now as when the fear or knowledg of man is removed, for a man freely to indulge himſelf a liberty of ſinning, is a high pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, and to make a practice of it, would argue a deſperate caſe; So when their ſinne cometh to be publick, it is the more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:61849:65"/>
being committed by them who ſhould have beene exemplary for Piety and Religion, do ſuffer in their ſinne, for want of ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. If ſo notable a Prophet as <hi>Moſes</hi> eſcaped not puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (for the Pſalmiſt ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.32</note> 
                  <hi>It went evil with him for the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites ſake,</hi>) though others provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him to ſinne; how much ſhall they be ſubject to Gods judgment, who by Ignorance or Scandal, cauſe Gods children to ſin?</p>
               <p n="3">§ 3. But howſoever an Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant or Scandalous Paſtor ought to be caſhiered; yet it is not in the peoples power to reject or relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh one that is already their Teacher, and ſeparate from Church-communion with him, except when he is utterly intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and all orderly meanes for his ejection do faile. It cannot be proved from Scripture that any people may reject or depoſe their Miniſters: much leſſe a leſſer part of a Church may do it, when the greater diſſenteth: No, nor a greater; becauſe it tendeth to confuſion. Mr. <hi>Baine</hi> telleth you, that Paſtor and people are as indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidually
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:61849:66"/>
joyned together, as hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and wife: That as no cauſe can ſeparate husband and wife, but Adultery, ſo nothing beſide inſufficiency (through ignorance or ſcandalous living) can ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Paſtor and people. For as he is ſacred in his firſt inſtalment, ſo in the performance of his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice he was honourable in the times of the Heathen. <hi>Tertullian</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">Tert. de Cor. Mil. c. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> that heathen Prieſts were crowned: A ſymbole that they could not be degraded, nor caſhiered. And the firſt Crown which the Romans uſed, was their <hi>Spicea Corona,</hi> given as a Religious Enſign in honour of their Prieſts. <hi>Honoſque is non niſi vitâ ſinitur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plinius Nat. Hiſt. lib. <hi>18.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp; exules etiam, cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toſque comitatur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Pliny:</hi> nought but death could terminate this honour; which was their companion both in exile and cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity.<note place="margin">Concil. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odic. cap. <hi>13</hi> Anno. <hi>320</hi>
                  </note> Sure I am, that it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed in an ancient Councel, That the people muſt not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to elect (and therefore not to reject) their Paſtor. If your Miniſter then be unable to teach you, do not admit him at firſt:
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:61849:66"/>
But if he be able to teach you, and guide you, be ruled by him, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in things that to you are doubtful; except he teach you any ſingular points; and then take the advice of other Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in trying it. Expect not that he ſhould humour you, and pleaſe your fancies, and ſay and do as you would have him. It is contrary, not only to all exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in any age of the Church, but to the office of Paſtors, and Duties of the people (in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture) to guide their Paſtors, and not to be guided by them, but to joyn with other Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on the Lords day, either in the forenoon or afternoon, as much as with their determined Pariſh or Congregation. Yet <hi>Nazianzen</hi> teacheth us,<note place="margin">Naz. Ep. <hi>26</hi>
                  </note> That he that thus deſpiſeth his Paſtor, is a vain man, and by reaſon of his preſumption, a new <hi>Dathan</hi> or <hi>Abiram.</hi> And we complain to the Lord in the words of the ſame holy Father; that it all our ſufferings this thing is the moſt ridiculous,<note place="margin">Naz. Ep. <hi>31</hi>
                  </note> and yet moſt to be pityed; that we are the ſame men that are injured
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:61849:67"/>
and accuſed: For ſome men ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject one thing againſt us, others another, according as their either mind, or manners, or miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous paſſions ſo ſuggeſt; and the moſt favourable men to us, do neglect or contemn us; and after we have ſpent our ſtrength and ſpirits for their good, they caſt us aſide as vile and diſhoneſt veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels. Thus <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> with whom we againe doe complaine,<note place="margin">Naz. Or. <hi>32</hi> Iren. Praeſ. l. <hi>1.</hi> n. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> that the world ſeeketh not Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, but Orators. And <hi>Irenaeus</hi> before him, ſheweth us, that it is the duty of a faithfull Paſtor to ſtudy the Truth, and not Eloquence. I remember that <hi>Sozomen</hi> writeth that <hi>Aetius</hi> (the Eunomian A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt) his Eloquence was to matchleſſe,<note place="margin">Soz. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>22.</hi> Euſ. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>31</hi>
                  </note> that it made his errour impregnable. And <hi>Euſebius</hi> reporteth, that <hi>Meletius</hi> the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick, for his eloquence was called, <hi>Mel Atticum,</hi> The hony of <hi>Greece.</hi> This I write, not for any evil eye I bear to them, that are gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with that gift of God: but that we muſt not with <hi>Moſes</hi> refuſe the meſſage from heaven, becauſe we are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and have not men
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:61849:67"/>
ſo glib a tongue as others: nor with <hi>Jonah</hi> turn our back becauſe the work may ſeem ungrateful. If he ſend us to labor among thorns, yet have we a gracious Maſter; his work is good, his end wil ſatisfie us: We ſhall then have the grapes and figs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jerem.</hi> 11.22.</note> which thornes and thiſtles would not yeeld us. Only I beſeech e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one to remember, that the complaints of Gods Meſſengers, though proceeding ſomewhat from heat of paſſion,<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 2.24.</note> are often ſeconded with diſmal and dreadful effects. The childhood of the children that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned <hi>Eliſha</hi> his Miniſtry, exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them not from puniſhment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it reſtrain'd them not from ſin.</p>
               <p n="4">§. 4. Hence it may appear, that the tying of our ſelves to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of Parochial Church-communion, doth not force any man to ſubmit to a weak Miniſter, when he might have a better. Chriſt hath taught us to ſeek after knowledg without the quenching of zeal; and to maintain zeale, without deſpiſing knowledge: To ſeek after truth in the way of Peace, and after Peace in the way of Truth; as knowing how
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:61849:68"/>
neere they dwell together.<note place="margin">Contra A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cad. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> Chriſtian Concord. p. <hi>35.</hi> &amp; <hi>36.</hi>
                  </note> And in the practice of this duty <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith Divinely, It is a farre leſſe ſin to be unlearned then unteachable.</p>
               <p>But for confirmation of this Aſſertion, I deſire the Reader to peruſe the diſcourſe of Reverend Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> whoſe words as my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended brevity doth not permit me to tranſcribe; So I note,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the publick welfare and unity of Chriſtian Churches, is to be preferred before the pleaſure, yea, or edifying of any ſingle member; and what confuſion will follow the plucking up of Chriſts, and the Magiſtrates, and the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches bounds.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If all the people may freely and lawfully joyn themſelves with that Church that hath the ableſt Teacher, then almoſt all the world muſt go to a few men, and leave the reſt;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 14.12.</note> then <hi>Barnabas</hi> may be forſoken, if <hi>Paul</hi> be the chief ſpeaker; and then able mens Churches will grow to that bigneſs that they will be no Churches, the Matter being too big for the End and Form.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That Miniſters are Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:61849:68"/>
as well as the people; and therefore every mans deſire muſt not deprive them of their Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; beſides that, the Lord aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigneth to every Paſtor a freedome to inſtruct a portion of his people: Gods work muſt be done before our own; and the ſaving of ſouls and propagation of the Goſpel, be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before our private comforts.</p>
               <p n="4">4. God hath more means then Miniſterial abilities, to encreaſe mens graces, and procure their ſalvation: for he that keeps in Gods order under a meaner ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Miniſter, is like to be a more humble thriving Chriſtian, then he that will break that order, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of edification: but God uſually chaſtiſeth men for ſuch diſorders, as we may ſee in daily experience. For God ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the ſame profeſſors (to our great hearts grief) to turn unto do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinal or practical evils, for their breaking Gods Order, and the Churches Unity. The ſpeciall work and duty required of every Miniſter,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.6. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.16 <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.3.4.</note> is to mind their people of their duty to God, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to mind God, and ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:61849:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>
him for his people. And for this purpoſe, the Paſtor (if faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) is not like the ſword-fiſh, which carries a weapon, but no heart: nor like the children of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> who being harneſſed and carrying bowes, wanted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and turned back in the day of battel. O what readineſſe and promptitude ſhould there be in people to have communion with ſuch Watchmen! The unwearied Miniſter of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.11</note> travels through all the Gardens of Learning, and ſucks ſomething from every ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that he may bring his veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and treaſures full of knowledg for the comfort of his hearers, but they will not hear.<note place="margin">Naz. Orat. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> Not only is his ſervice and office ſacred (for it is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Medi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aion between God and man) but his perſon,<note place="margin">Baſil. l. <hi>1</hi> in Pſal. <hi>44.</hi> Rom. <hi>10.15</hi>
                  </note> his very lips, which <hi>Baſil</hi> ſtileth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Lips of Chriſt, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle termeth his feete beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
               <p n="5">§. 5. Addreſſe your ſelves then in the Armour of God, all you meſſengers of God, to ſight here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after with the enemies of God.
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:61849:69"/>
Event hath ſealed Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> prophecie;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3.</note> The time is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy come, men ſtill not ſuffer wholeſome Doctrine. Unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table cenſures of ſtile, of method, of voice, of phraſe, of paſture, are but ſenſeleſſe imputations of the prophane multitude; far inferiour (if they were true) to the firſt Pouriſhes of a combate in earneſt. The worldlings heavy cenſure condemneth down-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight, both manner and matter, and the whole ſubſtance of your preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And for your perſons, you are not greater than <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt and our Saviour; ſooner therefore ſhal ye want a World, then a Theater, wherein, though the beſt do favour you, by moſt be ſure to be counted, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.12 13</note> what not? piacular, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilential, execrable fellowes. All the filthy ſcoffes and ſlanders that Satans Scavengers can take out of the ſinkes of all profeſſions, are thought over-clean to throw in their faces,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4 4</note> who would make the light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt to ſhine unto them. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:61849:70"/>
ſaid truly,<note place="margin">Hieron. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. ad De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metriadem.</note> 
                  <hi>Semper virtutibus contradicitur,</hi> vertues are ſtill contradicted. Pretend the world what the world can, here is the head and the heart of the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie: Contrariety breeds En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, Enmity cauſeth Separation, and Separation ſuppoſeth danger (from the party avoided) of infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p n="6">§. 6. But thou, O man of God, <hi>Tu ne cede malis, ſed contra audentior ito:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.21</note> be not overcome of evil, but overcome evil with good. Such an Antiperiſtaſis muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and enkindle zeale, if thy profeſſion depend not upon faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and thy conſcience upon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. For though Gods pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Spirit ſhould ſuſpend his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, yet canſt thou not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the reaſon of a man, and bruitiſhly be driven with the drove, much leſſe abandon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe; and without any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thine owne, like a nail in a wheel, only move as thou art moved, and turn as thou art tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. They who never once dreamed of ſalvation by Chriſt, held it not the leaſt part of their
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:61849:70"/>
glory to ſtirre a courſe like Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>podes, clean oppoſite to the liking of the multitude.<note place="margin">Phocion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pad Plut. Lacri. in Antiſt.</note> He in <hi>Plutarch</hi> applauded, ſuſpected his ſpeech; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; Hath any bad ſpeech fallen from my mouth without my knowledge? And <hi>Antiſthenes</hi> commended, was afraid of his Deeds; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: I am in agony, leſt I have done ſome miſchiefe. What in them without the law was voluntary, the ſame the law of Chriſt (if wee belive <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) impoſeth upon us as neceſſary; <hi>Recuſas eſſe in corpore,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. in Joan. tract. <hi>87.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſi non vis odium mundi ſuſtinere cum Capite:</hi> thou refuſeſt to be in the body, if thou wilt not ſuffer the hatred of the world with thy Head. Sure the currant credit of the godly in <hi>Gregory</hi> his time,<note place="margin">Greg. in Ezek. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> was, <hi>perverſorum rogatio, vitae noſtrae approbatio:</hi> Wicked mens detraction, is the approbation of our lives. And in all times the rebuke of Chriſt, was the Religion of Chriſtians.<note place="margin">Heb. <hi>11.</hi> per totum.</note> And as for our way of preaching, the Reverend Provincial Aſſembly
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:61849:71"/>
of <hi>London,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vindication ſet forth Nov. <hi>2. 1649.</hi> page <hi>82</hi>
                  </note> doth piouſly and judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly complaine, that though wee are farre from juſtifying any indiſcreet or paſſionate ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, yet we conceive it to be very hard meaſure, to have our integrity arraigned and condemned for humane infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. And wee hope, we may without boaſting, ſay thus much; That the ſetled Miniſtry of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> was never more cenſured, moleſted, impoveriſhed, and yet never more pious, peaceable, and painfull. Wherefore, that I may not number up numberleſs encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements, ſtand upon your guard within the limits of your daily warfare with the world; ſince faith is the victory that overcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the world.<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 5.4</note> Only conſider him that endured ſuch contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſinners.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12 3</note> 
                  <hi>Deus Pater Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tertul. ad Martyras, cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Xyſtarches Spiritus ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus, Epiſtates Jeſus Chriſtus; Corona aeternitatis, bravium; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicae ſubſtantiae politia in coelis, gloria in ſecula ſeculorum.</hi> He that hath ſaid, <hi>Be of good cheer, I have overcome the world, John</hi> 16.33. He is both Commander and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctator
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:61849:71"/>
of your combate, He is both Judge and Rewarder of your cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and conquerour of your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie; <hi>He will give you the Crowne of glory that fadeth not away.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Thirdly, Other imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and imaginated Pretences are anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</head>
               <p n="1">§. 1. ALthough all Divine Truths be precious, yet controverſies are ſo diſtaſtefull to me, that I reſolved againſt them. But he that made us, muſt rule us: and he that put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth us into the Vineyard, muſt meaſure out our work: and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth me to ſpeak briefly to the ſubſequent objections. For this is another Office of holy diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline: <hi>Non ſolum bona oſtendere,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:61849:72"/>
ſed mala refutare:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tert. Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. c. <hi>39.</hi>
                  </note> Not only by ſound doctrine to exhort, but likewiſe to convince the gainſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.9.</p>
               <p n="2">§. 2. Firſt, Some ſay, they ſeparate from a determined Church-communion, becauſe of diverſity of doctrine; as if they knew not where to find the truth. It is true,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. <hi>7.</hi> ult.</note> 
                  <hi>Solomon</hi> complaineth, That men have ſought many inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or imaginations; as in other things, ſo likewiſe in Doctrine, whereby men are drawn from the ſimplicity of their Creation. The Apoſtle likewiſe complaineth of a wind of doctrine,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.14.</note> whereby Chriſtians began to be blown from the ſtedfaſtneſſe of the Truth.<note place="margin">Auguſt. de civ. Dei lib. <hi>18.</hi> cap. Heb. <hi>13.9. 2</hi> Cor. <hi>2.17</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, that Satan ſeeing that Idolatrous ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges would downe, he bent his whole device in place of them to erect divers imaginations; that people in ſtead of images, might bow down to theſe, and worſhip them. Since which, it hath been his daily practice, either to broach divers and ſtrange doctrines ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of before: or to revive the old, and new dreſſe them;
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:61849:72"/>
and to mingle them (for that by themſelves they wil not utter) with the Apoſtolical doctrine, that ſo he might vent them. And this indeed is the diſeaſe of our age; and the juſt complaint we make of it. There hath good diſpatch been made of images; but ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations in their ſtead, are deified and worſhiped, carrying the Name and Credit of Apoſtolick Doctrine. To prevent this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, We are no where comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to Separate from Church-communion;<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 4.1. 1 <hi>Theſ</hi> 5.21</note> but to try the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; to prove all things; to hold faſt that which is good: and that we may do that, we are to pray, that he would open our eyes, that we may behold wondrous things out of his Law;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.18 <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.14.</note> and to pray for knowledge and underſtanding, and to endeavour to have our ſenſes exerciſed to diſcerne both good and evil. The advice that <hi>Syſinnius</hi> preſented to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Theodoſius</hi> (ſtudying how to put an end to the differences in diverſity of Doctrine,<note place="margin">Sozom. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> that then troubled the Church) was to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void all diſputations with Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:61849:73"/>
and to demand of them (when they petitioned him) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they would ſtand to the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuch as were Teachers in the Church, before it was divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? eſpecially, where their judgment diſſented not from the Scriptures.<note place="margin">Bp. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewes Ser. Worſhip i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginat.</note> Ancient Fathers thought it meet, that they that would take upon them to interpret the Scriptures, ſhould put in ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that the ſenſes they gave, ſhould be no other then the Church in former time had acknowledged. All that came after the Apoſtles, are commanded to labour for knowledg and learning,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5 12 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5 17 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.8.</note> and not to utter their own imaginations, or do deſire to be believed upon then bare word: for that were to have dominion of their Auditors Faith. <hi>Say I this of my ſelfe?</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>ſaith not the Law this alſo?</hi> Give I this ſenſe of mine own head, or hath not Chriſts Church heretofore given the like? Which one courſe if it were ſtrictly kept, would rid our Church of many falſe imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which now are ſtampt daily, becauſe every man upon his
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:61849:73"/>
owne ſingle bond is truſted to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the meaning of any Scripture.</p>
               <p n="3">§. 3. Secondly, Others pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, that they ſeparate from Church-communion for neglects and corruption in diſcipline. For anſwer to this: I would they read what their own Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> of New <hi>England</hi> writes: that the many notorious ſcandalous perſons that were found in the Churches of Iſrael,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Cottons Holineſſe of Church-members p. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> did only argue the neglect of Eccleſiaſtical diſcipline, in the toleration of ſuch publick ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals in the Church. And thus none of the men of God (who could not be ignorant of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches duty, and their ſin in ſuch neglects) ever attempted to Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from that which was in this ſort faulty. All was not right in the exerciſe of diſcipline, in the Churches, planted by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. The Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> was cenſured as very faulty, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2. So was the Church of <hi>Smyrna, Revel.</hi> 2.14. No leſſe faulty was the Church of <hi>Thyatyra, Rev.</hi> 2.20. Neither could the Church of <hi>Sardis</hi> be free, ſeeing the greateſt part were openly bad,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:61849:74"/>
there being but a few that had not defiled their garments, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.4. And yet nothing heard by way of advice for any to make ſeparation, nor reproof for their holding up Communion, nor any one inſtance of a ſeparatiſt given. And here Mr. <hi>Blake</hi> ſheweth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Blake Covenant c. <hi>31.</hi> p. <hi>238.</hi>
                  </note> that the godly non-conformiſt in England, who had a low opinion of the diſcipline then exerciſed, were ſo zealous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Church-ſeparation, that Mr. <hi>Parker,</hi> Mr. <hi>Paget,</hi> Mr. <hi>Ball,</hi> Mr. <hi>Brightman,</hi> and others, have left behind them large evidences of their zeale againſt ſeparation from Parochial Church Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies. It is more then ſtrange, that when the Apoſtles had by commiſſion from Chriſt planted Churches, and were to leave them to be propagated in future ages, yet would wholly be ſilent of this ſeparation, but leave us by our dark imaginations to diſcover it. In which, we are in danger to ſet our threſhold by Gods threſhold (of which hee ſadly complains;) or rather,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43 8.</note> juſtle out Gods threſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>old with ours.</p>
               <p n="4">§ 4. Thirdly, Others pretend
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:61849:74"/>
that they ſeparate from Parochial Church-communion for prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the people, and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in converſation. But neither doth this admit of ſeparation pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided that Doctrine be ſuch in which men may have communion for Edification. If we look upon the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> throughout the revolution of all times, we may find high Titles given them, even when they lived in all kind of ſin and Diſobedience. They had Titles given them of ſingular glory, by reaſon of priviledges,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.12. <hi>et</hi> 32.9. <hi>Zach.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4. <hi>Deut.</hi> 9.6. <hi>et</hi> 32.6. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.4. <hi>et</hi> 48.4. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 32.16.</note> which they enjoyed by their call into church-fellowſhip, as, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, Gods peculiar ones, his portion, his heritage, the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his eye, and many the like Elogies; In the mean time their Qualifications were as low, as their Titles high; their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation no wayes anſwering their calling, but branded to be ſtiff-necked, of an Iron ſinew, an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterous, a Sinful Nation, a People fooliſh and unwiſe, as <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> unto the Lord: And yet the Prophets and righteous perſons keep their reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:61849:75"/>
among them, held commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with them, and ſaw no ground of ſeparation from them. It ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a great contradiction to ſome, to name men at all believers, Saints, or Profeſſours, when their lives evidence an unſutableneſſe to ſuch a glory; yet we know the churches to whom Epiſtles are directed in Scripture,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. <hi>et.</hi> 6.7. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.20 <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.1.16</note> are ſo honoured, as we may ſee in their frontiſpieces: and the moſt upright hearted among them, had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with them, when yet they did wrong and defraud one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when they profaned the Lords Table, where Fornicators, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters, Luke-warme, &amp;c. And yet the Apoſtles did not leave them, but made it their buſineſſe to reclaim them. The advice that was ſometime given to a Maid, that for Religions ſake would retire her ſelfe to a ſolitary life; ſhe was told, <hi>Aut de fatuis Virginibus es, aut de prudentibus: ſi de fatuis, Congregatio tibi neceſſaria eſt; ſi de prudentibus, tu Congregationi:</hi> If ſhe were bad, ſhe need the city to better her; if good, the city needed her: So we may ſay to
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:61849:75"/>
the ſeparatiſts from Parochial-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations; either they ſtand in need of the Church, or the neceſſities of the Church call for their help and aſſiſtance.</p>
               <p n="5">§. 5. As for all other preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded cauſes of ſeparation, Learned <hi>Zanchius</hi> at length proveth,<note place="margin">Zanch. t. <hi>7.</hi> part <hi>2.</hi> col. <hi>74</hi> &amp;c.</note> that ſo great is the Authority of the Church viſible (whether Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal or Particular) that none may with hope of impunity, deſpiſe her Doctrine or Diſcipline, much leſſe ſeparate from her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion: becauſe to deſpiſe the Church, is to deſpiſe Chriſt; to divide the unity of the Church, is to divide Chriſt, and to cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him a freſh; and to ſeparate from the Church, is to ſeparate from Chriſt; for <hi>extra Eccleſiam non eſt Salus;</hi> out of the Church there is no ſalvation. Laſtly, if any doe pretend the practice of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain reformed Churches for Church ſeparation. I anſwer,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the piety and prudence of the Worthies of this Nation, was much more admirably valiant for the Lord, in eſtabliſhing Lawes with Penalties againſt this
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:61849:76"/>
profane licentiouſneſſe, then the practice of the contrary can be i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitable or warrantable.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.3.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">See Blond. Honor. Reg. &amp;c.</note>2. Forrain Churches were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo ſenſible of, nor had occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to bewail this prophaneneſſe, ſo much, as we in theſe laſt ſeven or eight years; wherein all the Ghoſts of the miſcreants of former ages, have been let looſe from hell, in full ſwarmes to infeſt this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, more then ever the locuſts did the Land of Egypt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We ought to follow others, no further then they are followers of Chriſt and his Goſpel. <hi>Non vivendum exemplit, ſed Legibus:</hi> And therefore I will not ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain what Orthodox Divines have in this point,<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> until our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries ſhall make it their ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k to prove ſome infirmity or inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency, in that which they have written.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:61849:76"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> Serious and frequent Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition ought to bee inculcated againſt this Errour.</head>
               <p n="1">§. 1. IT is very true, <hi>Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ſine quercla,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sen. de Ira c <hi>10.</hi> Salv. de G. D. l. <hi>8</hi> initio.</note> 
                  <hi>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntur aegra,</hi> you can never touch the ſore, without the grief of the Patient. All would be pleaſed, <hi>Nulli grata reprehenſio eſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salvian; None love reproof, none but the wiſe, Prov.</hi> 9.8. And that which is worſe; the moſt wicked caſt-away would rather heare his own falſe praiſes, then true reprehenſion; and be deceived with jeering applauſe, then ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by wholeſome Admonition. And yet Separatiſts from deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined Congregations, muſt no leſſe be admoniſhed, then other
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:61849:77"/>
ſinners; ſo long as there is any hope they will amend. That charge given to the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.9, 10. is ſix times al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in the New Teſtament, to warn them, <hi>that if they turne not, God will what his ſword,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.12</note> 
                  <hi>and be glorified in his juſtice upon them, who made no account of his mercy.</hi> And it is a juſt thing with God, when men wilfully winke, and ſhut their eyes againſt the light, to ſtrike them ſtark blind,<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 6 18 <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.11.</note> as he did the Aſſyrians, and the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites, and <hi>Elymas</hi> the Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerer, and to daſh out their eyes, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.28. It is true, Gods primary intention in ſending his meſſengers,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.15.</note> is for the good of his people; for he giveth them Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors according to his own heart, which do feed them with, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lede and underſtanding: yet in a ſecundary place, it is for to leave the wicked inexcuſable, and to juſtifie his proceeding toward them. See 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15, 16. <hi>John</hi> 9.39. Thus the Paſtor muſt do his duty, and referre the iſſue or ſucceſſe unto the Lord: yea, hee muſt deal plainly and roundly, as
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:61849:77"/>
the Lord himſelf doth, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 2.3, &amp;c. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.14. But chiefly with publick and common ſins (as this of Church-ſeparation is) leſt he ſeem to allow of them, and ſo become guilty of them by his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance. For,</p>
               <p n="2">§. 2 Though <hi>Saul</hi> acted not in the murder and Martyrdome of <hi>Steven,</hi> yet his conſent ſpake him guilty of the ſame crime.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 8.1.</note> A mind to tolerate evil, is ſin in the ſeed, which time bringeth forth, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.14, 15. God eſteemeth the evil we would do, as done, though we have not done it, and ſo juſtly puniſheth it. There is an adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the heart,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.28. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22 7.</note> and murder of the heart: <hi>Meritò autem malus puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Affectus, etiam cui non ſuccedit Effectus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine;</hi> deſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is an evil Affection puniſhed,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de civ. Dei lib. <hi>16.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> though the Effect (or Deed) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of follow not. They that allow of the evil which others do, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come guilty of the ſame ſin by their allowance. So were the Jewes guilty of all the blood ſhed by their Fathers from <hi>Abel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.35</note> ſo many yeeres before they had any being in the world: becauſe in
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:61849:78"/>
ſhedding innocent blood they ſhewed their conſent with them, who firſt did ſo. O that wee would conſider their eſtate, who are now pleaſed with all the injuries done to Gods ſervants;<note place="margin">Acts <hi>18.17</hi> Theod. in Jerem.</note> like <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio.</hi> But above all men, <hi>Duces eſſe principes erroris, eſt propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num;</hi> It is moſt prophane for Princes to be leaders into error, ſaith <hi>Theodoret.</hi> For the chief among the people to be ringleaders of this errour is deſperate. In regard of others, <hi>magnates ſunt magnetes,</hi> Great men have an attractive ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, like the loadſtone, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Potentes Patenter tormenta patientur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Jerome</hi> often: The mighty ſhall be mightily tormented. Oh that we could remember,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 32.9</note> that great men are not alwayes wiſe!</p>
               <p n="3">§. 3. It is a dangerous thing once to erre from the truth.<note place="margin">Arnob. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. Gent. lib. <hi>6</hi>
                  </note> There is in man a miſchievous ſelf-love, putting him on to defend his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, by erring more. <hi>Arno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> noteth well, <hi>Quod ſemel ſine ratione feciſtis, &amp;c.</hi> That which ye have once done without reaſon, ye defend, leſt ye ſhould ſeem to
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:61849:78"/>
have once been ignorant: Yee think it is better <hi>non vinci,</hi> not to be overcome, then to yield to a confeſſed truth. But a true Chriſtian will rejoyce and ſay, <hi>Ut ille mei Victor eſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cecilius a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Minut. Felic.</note> 
                  <hi>ita ego mei Triumphator erroris:</hi> as my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary hath conquered mee, ſo I triumph over my errour. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of our Miniſtry in this Church-ſeparation, produceth a wilfull ſhutting the eyes againſt the light of the Goſpel, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away all ability of believing to ſalvation. They could not believe (<hi>John</hi> 12.39.) that is, ſay <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> and <hi>Theophylact;</hi> They would not. They will not indeed believe: Nor is it in ſuch a mans power to be willing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.6.</note> For as Faith is the gift of God, ſo is a true and hearty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thereof, which God beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on them only, whom hee will therein ſatisfie and make bleſſed: and juſtly giveth not unto thoſe who undervalue his mercies, and deſpiſe appointed Ordinances. Oh be not then like thoſe obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate men, who will not hear their appointed Paſtor, bur wilfully
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:61849:79"/>
ſtop their ears, and ſhut their eyes, that they may the more ſecurely run upon their owne deſtruction, and neither hear nor ſee that which might ſtay them, and make for their converſion and ſafety.<note place="margin">Hippocr. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor.</note> Deafneſſe in a ſharp Fever (ſay Phyſicians) is a ſign of madneſſe: more miſerable are obſtinate ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. The lunatick have ſome excuſe; the Will is not in the fault, where men are not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſaith <hi>Salvian.</hi> The more condemnable are thoſe,<note place="margin">Salv. de g. D. lib. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Qui ſani inſaniunt,</hi> who are wittingly mad. Where there is wilful maliciouſneſs, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, there is abſence of Grace, ſaith <hi>Cyril Hieriſolymit.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cyril. Hier. Catech. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> Therefore God juſtly deſerteth thoſe, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly firſt deſert him, following their obſtinacy, by giving them up to ſpiritual blindneſſe, withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the common light which he had given them. His judgments ever follow, never precede mens ſinnes: where his external decree and om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcience precede, it is to appoint impenitent ſinners to puniſhment, not to ſin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:61849:79"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> Some Antidotes againſt the Infection of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochiall Church Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</head>
               <p n="1">§. 1. IT hath ever been Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans policy to begin in perſwading men to Worldlineſſe, Fleſh-pleaſing, Security, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, and utter neglect of God and their ſouls, at leaſt by prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their bodies and worldly things: but where this will not take, but God awakeneth men ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually, he next ſetteth them on a Religion not commanded; and would make poor ſoules believe, they do nothing,<note place="margin">Mr. Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. direct. <hi>26.</hi> pag. <hi>352.</hi>
                  </note> if they do not more then God hath commanded them; and unleſſe they ſeparate from their appointed and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:61849:80"/>
Church-communion. When Satan hath no other way to deſtroy Religion and Godlineſſe, he will pretend to be Religious and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly himſelf; and then he is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies over-religious, and over-godly in his materials. It is true, a man cannot ſerve God too much, formally and ſtrictly conſidering his ſervice, much leſſe love him too much: but we may do too much materially, intending thereby to ſerve God; which though it be not true Rigteouſneſſe, yet being intended for Righteouſneſſe, and done as a ſervice unto God, is by <hi>Solomon</hi> called Over-much Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe:<note place="margin">Eccleſ. <hi>7.16</hi> Eng. Ann. in loc.</note> where Interpreters conceive, the Name of the mean, is given to the extreme. For a man may many times do a thing conſcienſciouſly, and upon an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of duty, and thereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve himſelf in much ſinne, and ſorrow: when indeed there was no neceſſity ſo to doe: As 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.21. <hi>Acts</hi> 26.9.</p>
               <p n="2">§ 2 I know it is ſtark madneſſe in the profane ſecure world, to think the doing of no more then God hath commanded us, is do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:61849:80"/>
too much, and more then needs: but this is to blaſpheme the moſt high,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.10.</note> by denying his Goodneſſe, his Wiſdome, his juſt Government; to blaſpheme his Lawes, as too ſtrict or preciſe; and to reproach his holy waies, as if they were grievous, intolerable or unneceſſary. Much more is their madneſs, in charging the godly with being too pure, and making too great a ſtir for heaven, and that meerly for godlineſſe and obedience; when (alas) the beſt fall too ſhort of what Gods Word, and the neceſſity of their own ſouls do require; that their conſciences do more grievouſly accuſe them of negligence, then the barking world doth of being too diligent. Yet much more mad are world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, to lay out ſo much time,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark</hi> 8.36</note> and care, and labour for earthly vanities, and to think that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and eternal happineſſe, and the eſcaping of everlaſting damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are matters not worth ſo much adoe: but may be had with a few cold wiſhes; that no labour ſhould be thought too much for the world, fleſh, and the divel, and
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:61849:81"/>
every little is enough for God. Yet <hi>Quiſquis plus juſto non ſapit, ille ſapit:</hi> that is, in our Saviours phraſe;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.16.</note> 
                  <hi>We are as ſheep in the midſt of Wolves, wee had need then be wiſe as Serpents, and harmeleſſe as Doves.</hi> It was the commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Agricola</hi> in <hi>Tacitus; Reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuit (quod eſt difficillimum) ex Sapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia modum:</hi> He kept a medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critie in his Wiſdome.<note place="margin">Lactant. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſaith, <hi>Neque Religio ulla ſine ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia ſuſcipienda eſt, neque ulla ſine Religione probanda ſapientia:</hi> no Religion ſhould be undertaken without wiſdom, neither ſhould any wiſdome be allowed without Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. For all overdoing in Gods work is undoing, as ſaith a late redoubted Warrier of the Lord:<note place="margin">Mr. Baxt. Direct. <hi>26.</hi> pag. <hi>352.</hi>
                  </note> And whoever you meet with that would overdo, ſuſpect him either a ſubtil deſtroyer, or one deluded by the deſtroyer, Oh what a Tragedy could I here ſhew you of the divels acting! And what a myſterie of the Helliſh art of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving could I open! By occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our preſent quarrels with hereticks, the Old Serpent ſteps in, and will needs be a ſpirit of
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:61849:81"/>
zeale, in cauſing many profeſſours to ſeparate from their appointed congregations; and inducing them (or rather ſeducing them) to overdo. O that God would open the eyes of his churches in <hi>England</hi> to ſee this Satanical ſtratageme.</p>
               <p n="3">§. 3 Then let us not be too much bent on a thing,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.3.</note> nor juſt in our own opinion: but let us tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per our zeal with godly wiſdome, adviſe with others, lean not on our own underſtanding, flatter not our ſelvs in any opinionative confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of our own abilities to judg of all that is fit to be done: but think ſoberly of our ſelves. The more humble thou are, the more wary and circumſpect thou wilt be; and the more wary, the more ſafe. Now for the avoiding of overdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in the point in hand, let us conſtantly practiſe theſe few Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Labour for knowledge and a ſound underſtanding:<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.7.</note> a ſound Judgment is a moſt precious mercy, and much conduceth to the ſoundneſſe of Heart and Life.<note place="margin">Aug. de C. D. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Male vivitur ſi de Deo non bene creditur.</hi> A weak Judgment is
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:61849:82"/>
eaſily corrupted: And if it be once corrupted, the will and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation will quickly follow. Our underſtandings are inlets of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance to the whole ſoule. The moral Philoſopher hath well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded,<note place="margin">Derodon. diſp. <hi>1.</hi> in Ethicis. <hi>§ 4</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Omnis malus eſt ignorans, &amp; ſolus ignorans malus eſt;</hi> igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is virtually every er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Be ſure you make conſcience of the great duties you are to perform in your families: Teach your children and ſervants the Knowledge and fear of God: pray with them daily and fervent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: Read the Scriptures and good books to them: Keep them from ſin; eſpecially ſee that the Lords day be wholly ſpent in theſe exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, and not in ſports or idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Remember alwaies that ye are bound to be followers of Peace and unity: He that is not a ſon of peace, is not the ſon of God. All other ſins deſtroy church-communion conſequenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,<note place="margin">Dial cum Trapertit. pag. <hi>265.</hi>
                  </note> but diviſion and ſeparation de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſh it directly. <hi>Juſtin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> profeſſeth, that if a Jew ſhould
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:61849:82"/>
keep the ceremonial Law (ſo hee did not perſwade the Gentiles to it as neceſſary) yet if he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg Chriſt, he judgeth that he may be ſaved, and he would have communion with him as a brother. And I profeſſe, that I believe, that profeſſors which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb the peace of the church, and ſeparate from their brethren; nay I fear, leſt they ſhould prove a fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand in hell, for being a fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand in the church.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Keep the maſtery o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver your fleſh and ſenſes. Few fall from God, but fleſh-pleaſing is the cauſe; Remember who hath ſaid, <hi>If ye live after the fleſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.5, 6, 7 <hi>&amp;</hi> 13, 14</note> 
                  <hi>ye ſhall die.</hi> Think of this when ye are tempted, not only to luſt, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, worldlineſs, &amp;c. but alſo when ye are tempted to ſeperate from your Parochial Aſſemblies: for the Apoſtles hath pronounced ſuch to be carnal. You little think what a ſin it is, even to pleaſe your fleſh further then it tends to help you in the ſervice of God.<note place="margin">Seneca I. p. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Multis enim ſervict, qui corpori ſervit;</hi> He hath many maſters, that ſerves his fleſh; and after
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:61849:83"/>
                  <hi>Honeſtum ei vile eſt, cui corpus charum eſt;</hi> Honeſtie is vile to him that endeareth his body. Happy, were many a Chriſtian, if they had learned this leſſon, which an infidel teacheth them; then would they beware, leſt conſcience loſe its tenderneſſe; then would they live in a conſtant readineſſe and expectation of death, having their converſation in heaven, while they live upon earth.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Look upon all preſent actions or conditions with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of their end.<note place="margin">Plutar. de Adulat. &amp; Ambit.</note> 
                  <hi>Solon</hi> deſired <hi>Croeſus,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to behold the end. Deſire not a ſhare in their proſperity, who muſt pay as dear for it, as the loſſe of their ſouls: Be not ambitious of that honour which muſt end in confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: nor of the favour of thoſe that God will call enemies. Fear not that man that muſt ſhortly tremble before God, whom all muſt fear.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, Deal faithfully with every truth you receive; take heed of ſubjecting it to carnall intereſt. If once you have affections that
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:61849:83"/>
can maſter your underſtandings, you underſtand not the Truth. This changeth Chriſtians into Males or Aſſes:<note place="margin">Soz l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> as <hi>Antony</hi> the Hermite dreamed of the <hi>Arians.</hi> For when you have a reſolution to caſt off any duty (as Parochial Church-communion) you will firſt believe it is not duty. And when you muſt change you judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for carnal advantages, you wil make the change ſeem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and right. And evil ſhall be proved good, when you have a mind to follow it.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Apprehended and neceſſity and uſefulneſſe of Chriſts Officers, Order, and Ordinances for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of his Church. Tell your <hi>Archippus</hi> that he fulfill his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Concil. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lev.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 24 25. <hi>Anno</hi> 416.</note> as in abandoning all ſin in converſation, ſo all errors in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: otherwiſe by the ancient canons of the Church he hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited his miniſtry. Paſtors muſt guide you, not ſeduce you, or lead you Jeſuitically blindfolded <hi>caecâ obedientiâ</hi> Pray for you Miniſter that utterance may be given him,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.19</note> that he may open his mouth boldly to make known the myſtery of the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:61849:84"/>
Goſpel. Watch carefully, that no weakneſſe of the Miniſter draw you to a diſeſteeme of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God, nor any of the ſad miſcarriages of Profeſſors ſhould cauſe you to ſet leſſe by Truth or Godlineſſe: Wrong not Chriſt more, becauſe other men have ſo wronged him; Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel more with your owne unfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and unworthineſs in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, then with other mens. It is the frame of your own heart, that doth more to help or hinder your edification, then the quality of thoſe whom you joine with.</p>
               <p n="4">§ 4 But the ſad experience of theſe times of ſeparation from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined church-communion, hath much abated the confidence of the godly, that Antidotes wil prevail with the vulgar or ordinary Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian: and cauſed them to have lower thoughts of mens docility and tractability, then ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they have had, and doe look on man as a diſtempered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant creature,<note place="margin">Ariſt. Eth. lib. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi> in ſine.</note> of a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral mutability in his apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Affections: though
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:61849:84"/>
God, who knowes the heart, and knowes his owne decrees, may know his ſincerity, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>know his perſeverance. The fruit of Church-ſeparation, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareath, that now when Satan hath a deſign to burn up the Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of Learning and R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ligion, how few are watering Gods plants? when the greedy mouth of ſacriledg is gaping for their mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, how few are voluntarily adding for the ſupply of its defect! when the Goſpel is ſo under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, the Miniſtry ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligned, and their maintenance ſo envied; how few are they that appeare for them? How few are like that Noble man, who publickly tore and rent the impious Edict of <hi>Diocleſian</hi> the Emperour againſt Criſtians?<note place="margin">Euſeb. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>5</hi>
                  </note> What God will yet do with us, we cannot tell: but if he will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue his Goſpel to us, theſe few may have the greater comfort in it: if hee will forſake a proud and unworthy people, yet may theſe few ſouls have comfort of their ſincere endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, they may eſcape the gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:61849:85"/>
of conſcience, and the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick curſe and reproach which the hyſtory of this age may faſten up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them who would either in ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant fury, or malicious ſubtilty, or baſe temporizing cowardize, oppunge or undermine the Goſpel; or in perfidious ſilence look on, whilſt it is deſtroyed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:61849:85"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> The Concluſion.</head>
               <p n="1">§ 1. HAving taken the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to deliver my Reaſons againſt this common Sin and Error: I humbly crave, that if ever Chriſtians would have their ſoules converted, they would la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to frequent Divine Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances in their due circumſtances. If we look to the quality of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Sam. <hi>13.18</hi> Arn. contra Serapien.</note> 
                  <hi>Saul</hi> did well (ſaith <hi>Arno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi>) when he offered Sacrifice unto God: But we muſt not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the quality of the Fact, but the Pride of the contemner; for there are many Duties, <hi>Quae cum bona fint opera, perniciem pariunt, cum non eo ordine, quo ſunt conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuta, peraguntur:</hi> Which, though they be good works, bring dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, when they are not done in that order as they ſhould. No man will be much wrought on by that which he deſpiſeth. The great
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:61849:86"/>
cauſes of this contempt are, a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Judgement, and a graceleſſe Heart. It is no more wonder for a Soul to loath Divine Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that ſavoureth not their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Nature, then it is for a ſick man to loath his food. Where a ſanctified Judgment is wanting, the moſt helliſh Vice may ſeem a Vertue, and the moſt ſacred Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Divine Inſtitution may ſeem as the waters of Jordan to <hi>Naaman.</hi> Oh! How many Soules may curſe thoſe wretches in Hell fire for ever, that have by them been brought to contemn the Meanes that ſhould ſave them! And let the greateſt that are guilty in this crime,<note place="margin">Cyprian E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. <hi>72.</hi>
                  </note> read <hi>Cyprian</hi> his words, and tremble. What grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter crime can there be (ſaith he) then to have ſtood up againſt Chriſt (In his Officers and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances)? Then to have ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the church of Chriſt, which he hath purchaſed with his blood? Then to have fought by the fury of hoſtile Diſcord againſt the una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly agreeing people of God? Who though themſelves ſhould repent, and turn to the church,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:61849:86"/>
yet can they not recover and bring back with them, thoſe ſeduced by their Example; or thoſe that being by death prevented, are dead without the church, whoſe Souls at the day of Judgment ſhall be required at their hands, who were the Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of them to Perdition, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">§ 2. And now I have given you my beſt advice, for the avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this Error. The manner of it is imperfect, and too much mine own: but for the main mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I dare ſay, I received it from God, in his Holy Scriptures. And from him I deliver it to his People, and his charge I lay upon them, that they entertain and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe it. Yet I know there is a remnant of Paganiſme and Infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in the beſt of chriſtians con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Divine Authority of the Sacred Scriptures.<note place="margin">Auguſt. de Fide &amp; Op. c. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> The chief cauſe (beſides many others) which perverteth the Underſtandings of men in this point, in my poor ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, is this. When men have deeply wounded their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences by ſinning againſt Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and given the Victory to their fleſhly Luſts, ſo that they
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:61849:87"/>
muſt either deeply accuſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn themſelves, or deny the Scriptures; they chooſe that which ſeemeth the more tolerable and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireable to them: and ſo, rather condemn the Scriptures, then themſelves. Theſe are, <hi>Lucifuga Scripturarum</hi> (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> calls them) Owles or Bats;<note place="margin">Tert. de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur. Carn. c. <hi>47.</hi>
                  </note> which can no more take heed unto that light that is the Life of the World, then Bats do unto the light of the Sun. And what Malefactor would not do the like, and except againſt the Law that doth condemn him, if that would ſerve his turn? And when men, that are engaged in a ſinful courſe, do ſee that the Word of God doth ſpeak ſo terribly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, they dare not live in that ſinne, while they believe the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, becauſe it is ſtill wakning and galling their guilty conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: but when they have either caſt away their Belief of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, or otherwiſe miſtaken them through miſinterpretation, miſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, &amp;c. then conſcience will let them ſin with more quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. The like may be expected from thoſe I oppoſe. For theſe
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:61849:87"/>
men refuſe their Phyſick, becauſe it is unpleaſant, and not becauſe it is unwholeſome: yet at laſt their Appetite ſo maſtereth their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that they will not believe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing can be wholeſome, which goes ſo much againſt their ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack. <hi>Ahab</hi> believed not the meſſage of <hi>Micajah;</hi> not becauſe he ſpake falſly,<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.8.18.</note> but becauſe hee ſpake no good of him, but evill. Men will eaſily be drawn to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that to be true, which they would faine have to be true; and that to be falſe, which they deſire ſhould be falſe. But alas! how ſhort and ſilly a cure is this for a guilty Soule? And how ſoone will it leave them in uncurable Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery!</p>
               <p n="3">§ 3. Only I muſt crave this of the Reader, that my confeſſed weakneſſe be no prejudice to Gods Truth: and that he will not judge of the cauſe by the Perſon, nor take the Name or Perſon for a Fault: Which is the thing that the ancient chriſtians did ſo depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate of the Pagans; and therefore I hope every Chriſtian will grant. For in regard of the churches pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:61849:88"/>
neceſſities, I dare not give over, for all my Imperfections. Though I have ever been of a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit too eaſily diſcouraged, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſay as the Prophet, <hi>I will ſpeak no more in his Name:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.9.</note> yet God hath ſo ſuited his Providence to my Infirmities and Neceſſities, as not only to cure my backward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but alſo to convince me of the pleaſantneſſe of his Work. I am aſſured that it was the Lord that ſent me into his Vineyard, and without him none ſhall force me out.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.16.</note> He that gave me fewer Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents then others, will Expect but an anſwerable Improvement at my hands: but be they never ſo ſmall, I dare not hide them. He that calleth for two Mites, will accept them:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25. <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.10.</note> Hee deſpiſeth not the day of ſmall things. Hee ſometime revealeth that to <hi>babes,</hi> which he hideth from the <hi>wiſe and prudent: For the Wiſdome of the World is fooliſhneſs with God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.25.</note> 
                  <hi>and the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſs of God is wiſer then men: and no fleſh ſhall glony in his ſight.</hi> The Lord grant, that I may ſo uſe the ſmall abilities that I have, that I be not condemned as an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:61849:88"/>
and unfaithful Servant: and then I do not feare being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for their ſmalneſs.</p>
               <p n="4">§ 4. More I would ſay, but I feare to ſpoile the elegancy or lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Camero,</hi> in his Epiſtle <hi>ad Theologos Leidenſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Can. pag. <hi>720.</hi> folio.</note> by Engli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing it: wherein is the ſumme of what I would ſay, and thither I refer the Reader. In the mean time, look upon my aberrations, where you find them, with pity and Pardon; And where you ſhew me that I have erred (as a man) you ſhall ſee that as a Chriſtian, it was not my want of love to the Truth, but want of light to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover it, that hath miſled me from it My Prayer is, that the Lord would ſave his People from that ſpirit of Pride, hypocriſie, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, and Giddineſſe, which is of late gone forth, and is now deſtroying and making havock of millions of Soules in <hi>England.</hi> And that the Lord would keep his People unſpotted of the guilt of thoſe Sinnes, which in theſe dayes have been the ſhame of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and have made us a Scandal and Scorn to the World.</p>
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:61849:89"/>
               <p>And pardon, O Lord, thy Servants Sin,: for I do daily diſhonour thy Holyneſſe, and diſgrace thy Work and Service by my weakneſs and unworthineſſe. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile from my heart, that my Apprehenſions are ſo dull, my Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions ſo ſtupid, and my Expreſſions ſo law and unbeſeeming thy Service. Remember with whom thou haſt to do. What canſt thou expect from duſt, but levity? or from corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but defilement? I know thou wilt be ſain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified in them that come nigh thee. And before all the people thou wilt be glorified. But though weakneſſe and irreverence be the fruit
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:61849:89"/>
of mine own Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yet the fire is from thy Altar, and the work is of thy commanding. Oh therefore waſh away all my Sins with the blood of the Lamb, which taketh away the Sin of the world. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect or none, muſt be they Service here. Oh take thy Sons excuſe; <hi>The Spirit is willing, but the Fleſh is weak.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Gratias tibi Domine Jeſu.</closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:61849:90" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:61849:91"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:61849:91"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:61849:92"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:61849:92"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:61849:93"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:61849:93"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:61849:94"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:61849:94"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:61849:95"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:61849:95"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:61849:96"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:61849:96"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:61849:97"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:61849:97"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:61849:98"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:61849:98"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:61849:99"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:61849:99"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:61849:100"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:61849:100"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:61849:101"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:61849:101"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:61849:102"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:61849:102"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:61849:103"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:61849:103"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:61849:104"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:61849:104"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:61849:105"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:61849:105"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:61849:106"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:61849:106"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:61849:107"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:61849:107"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:61849:108"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:61849:108"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
